<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A moste necessary treatise of free wil not onlye against the Bapistes, but also against the Anabaptistes, which in these our daies, go about to renue the detestable heresies of Pelagius, and of the Luciferians, whiche say and affirm, that we be able by our own natural strength to fulfil the law and commaundementes of God. Made dialoge wyse by Iohn Veron, in a manner word by woorde, as he did set it forth in his lectures at Paules.</title>
            <author>Véron, John, d. 1563.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1561</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 180 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 89 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14366</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24684</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101311</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837127</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837127</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1437</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14366)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1437)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1475-1640 ; 979:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A moste necessary treatise of free wil not onlye against the Bapistes, but also against the Anabaptistes, which in these our daies, go about to renue the detestable heresies of Pelagius, and of the Luciferians, whiche say and affirm, that we be able by our own natural strength to fulfil the law and commaundementes of God. Made dialoge wyse by Iohn Veron, in a manner word by woorde, as he did set it forth in his lectures at Paules.</title>
                  <author>Véron, John, d. 1563.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[176] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By John Tisdale, and are to be sold at his shop in Lombard streate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1561]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name and address from colophon; publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Against fre wil men.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A ² A-K.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Predestination --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1437:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1437:1"/>
            <p>¶A moſte neceſſary treatiſe of free wil, not onlye againſt the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes, but alſo againſt the Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſtes, which in theſe our daies, go about to renue the deteſtable here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies of <hi>Pelagius,</hi> and of the <hi>Luciferians,</hi> whiche ſay and affirm, that we be able by our own natural ſtrength to fulfil the law and commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of God.</p>
            <p>¶Made dialoge wyſe by <hi>Ihon Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron,</hi> in a manner word by woorde, as he did ſet it forth in his lectures at Paules.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1437:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1437:2"/>
            <head>¶To the righte hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Lorde, my Lorde Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Dudly, maſter of the horſes, and knight of the moſt honorable order of the Garter. Ihon Veron wiſheth grace, peace of conſcience, with encreaſe of honor, from God the father, through his ſon Ieſus chriſt our Lord.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or, as much, as I haue all ready ſet fourthe, the doctrine of predeſtinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and of the deuine pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uidence of God, wherein I haue ſtrongly proued by manifeſt textes of the ſcriptures, and ſufficient au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thorities of the aunciente wryters of the primitiue church, that God hath from the beginninge, orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and appoynted ſome, for to be felow heyres with his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, of his heauenly kingdome, and ſome again to be euerlaſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye dampned in hell fire: and that whome he hath ordeined before, to
<pb facs="tcp:1437:3"/> enioy and poſſeſſe euerlaſting life, them he hathe choſen in hys ſonne Ieſu Chriſt, afore the foundacions of the worlde were laide, whiche thynge he dyd of hys free mercye and goodneſſe, and withoute anye reſpecte at all of their owne deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinges or merits, for to ſetforthe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory of his grace, &amp; to declare hys mercy throughe oute al the whole world: but whome he hath apoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be the veſſels of hys wrathe, them he hathe accordinge to hys ryghteous and vnſerchable iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente ſtyrred vp for to be the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of hys iuſtice, and for to be glorifyed by their dampnatyon, wherin he dothe them no manner of wrong, ſithe that he rewardeth them, accordinge to theyr naturall corruption, whiche they haue of their parent Adam, wherbi we are all in generall, ſubiecte to euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting damnation, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if he ſhoulde damne vs all, he ſhoulde do vs but right, and no iuſte occaſyon at all,
<pb facs="tcp:1437:3"/> could we haue, to complain of him or of his moſt righteous iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t I haue thought it good and expedi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ent, for to adde vnto it, the mooſte neceſſarye doctrine of free wyll. Whiche as it dothe altogether de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend of the other, and is moſt ſure<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye grounded in it, ſo it can not be ſubſtantially vnderſtanded, wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome ſight and knowledge of the ſame, as it doth euidentlye ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by thoſe, which plainely af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrme that, onleſſe we haue free wyl, vertue ſhall not be rewarded, nor the workes of the ſaints crow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned: which if they would conſyder from what beginning, the doctrin of Predeſtination dothe fetche the glorye of the ſaintes, they ſhoulde ſone eſpy out theyr owne erroure. Whome (ſayeth the Apoſtle) God hathe choſen, them did he cal, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hathe called, them did he iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye, and whome he hathe iuſtified, them did he glorify. Wherfore the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by the ſayinge of the Apoſtle, are
<pb facs="tcp:1437:4"/> the faythfull crowned wyth eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and euerlaſting glory?<note place="margin">Why the faithfull are crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye.</note> becauſe forſothe, that by the fre mercye of God, and not by theyr owne indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, they be both choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, called and iuſtified. Heare doe we learne, in theſe fewe words, that all the hole glory of our ſaluation, ought only to be geuen and attributed vnto the free election of God, whereof doth proceade, come and ſprynge, bothe the will and power, that we haue, to do any thing, that is good and acceptable before the maieſtye of our heauenly father. Yea before we be renewed by the holy ghoſt, and made newe creatures in oure ſauioure Ieſu Chriſte, we are the ſeruauntes of ſynne. What fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome then canne we iuſtlye boaſte or bragge of? <hi>Vbi ſpiritus domini,</hi> ſayeth ſaynte Paule,<note place="margin">ii. Co. iii</note> 
               <hi>ibi libertas:</hi> where the ſpirite of the Lorde is, there is libertye and fredome.<note place="margin">Ioh. viii.</note> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: <hi>Si vos filius liberauerit, vere li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beri eritis,</hi> that is to ſay:</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1437:4"/>
            <p>If the ſonne doth delyuer you, ye ſhall be free in deede.<note place="margin">What we are as long, as we be voide of the ſpirit of God.</note> Theſe ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges, do ſufficiently declare, that as long as we are voide of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God and are not yet ſet at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty by the ſonne, we are nought els but the bond ſlaues of Sathan the dyuell of ſyn &amp; of deathe. Many other places of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures, might I heare aleadge, which do teache that of oure ſelues, we be not able to think a good thought. But leſt, I ſhould be tedious vnto your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Lordſhip, I wyll omytte them, and ſhew brieflye, what the Concil of Myluente did moſt god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye and catholikely decree and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termyne touching this matter:<note place="margin">Sinodus mileuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tana.</note> If any man (ſaye the holye fathers gathered in that Concyll) dothe affyrme,<note place="margin">Note ye wel thoſe things ye free wyll men.</note> that we canne by the vertue and ſtrength of oure owne nature thinke or chuſe, as it is expedyente, anye good thynge that pertayneth to oure ſaluation, or agree and conſent to the whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome
<pb facs="tcp:1437:5"/> preachinge of the goſpell, without the illuminating, and in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpiration of the holye ghoſt, who geueth vs a pleaſure or ſwetneſſe in conſentinge, and the truthe in beleuinge, he is deceaued with an heretical ſpirit, not vnderſtanding the voyce of God, ſayinge in the goſpell: without me, ye can do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge,<note place="margin">Iohn. xv.</note> nor the ſayinge of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtell,<note place="margin">ii. Co. iii.</note> where he ſayeth: Not that we be able to thinke any thinge of oure ſelues, as of our ſelues, But our ſuffiencye or ableneſſe is of God. Again: If any man doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiouſlye maintaine, that God doth tarye for oure wyll, that we maye be purged from ſynne, and doth not confeſſe, that by the infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and working of the holy ghoſt it is wrought in vs, that we be wil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling to be purged, he doth reſiſte &amp; withſtand the holy ghoſt him ſelf, ſayinge by Salomon: The wil, is prepared of the lord. And alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle,<note place="margin">Philip. ii</note> which preacheth whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomelye,
<pb facs="tcp:1437:5"/> that it is God,<note place="margin">Auguſt. ad Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plici.</note> that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in vs both the wyll, and the worke, according to his good wil. Wher the Apoſtell doth ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlye ſhewe, that the wil it ſelfe, is made good in vs, by the workinge of God. For, if we ſhuld aſke, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the good wil, is a gift of god, or not, I maruail, if any man dirſt ſay nay.<note place="margin">Here we do learne that we can not pray vnto god with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>oute the eſpeciall grace of God. Eſa. lxv. Rom. x.</note> Moreouer (ſay the fathers afore reherced) If any man dothe ſaye, that the grace of God, can be geuen by humaine inuocation, or mans calling vpon god, &amp; not that the grace it ſelfe dothe worke or bringe to paſſe, that God is called vppon of vs, he dothe gayneſaye Eſaye the prophet, or the Apoſtell ſpeaking the ſame: I am founde of them, that ſoughte me not, and dyd appeare playnely vnto them, that dyd not aſke of me. What canne be ſpoken more playnelye of the vnableneſſe of manne afore hee be regenerated or borne of newe by the ſpyryte of God?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1437:6"/>
            <p>All men maye eaſely ſee by theſe ſayinges, whiche are moſte ſurely grounded in the worde of the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge God, what wyl and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the we haue of oure ſelues, to doe any thinge, that pertaineth eyther to the glory of God, or to our own ſaluation. Therefore, I can not but maruaile at our pope pelagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans and at the viperous broode of the fre wyll men whych do ſtyll to the greate iniurye of the gratuite and free grace of God,<note place="margin">The pope pela<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gians and the viperous broode of the free wil men.</note> ſo ſet oute boaſt and aduaunce the free wyll and ſtrength of man, whyche (as ſainte Auguſtyne ſayeth) is verye ſore hurte and wounded, whych is all to ſhaken, and loſt, hauinge more nede of a true confeſſion tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a falſe defence. Againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now at this preſent, beinge forced ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto by the great loue &amp; vehement zeale that I beare vnto the truth, I haue taken vppon me for to wryte, that ſo I maye ſomewhat releue and helpe the poore ſimple
<pb facs="tcp:1437:6"/> and ignoraunte, whome by theyr peſtiferous doctrine they cauſe for to leaue the ſure ſtai,<note place="margin">To ſtaye vpon free wil, is to leane vp the broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rede of Egipte.</note> that we haue in the free mercy and grace of god and to leane vpon the broken rede of theyr free will. Whyche is the next way, that Sathan the deuell, the enemy of our ſaluation can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe, for to throw them headlonge into the bottomleſſe pit of eternall dampnation. Theyr argumentes, which they do ſo gaily paynt out, wyth wraſted textes of the ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, I haue diligently confuted, not ſticking, as occaſion did ſerue, to borowe of other, whiche haue foughte agaynſt that monſtruous hereſye before me, thoſe thynges, whych I iudged mete for my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. For, when we haue an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to ouercom, it maketh no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter whether we ouercome hym, wyth ſ newe weapon, that was neuer occupyed before, or wyth a weapon that hath bene all readye occupyed of other. In temporall
<pb facs="tcp:1437:7"/> warres, what dothe it ſkill, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we beate downe the common ennemy, with our owne weapon, or with our felowes weapon? So that he be beate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> down &amp; ouercom, it is all one thinge. We al oughte to ſeeke the glorye of God, and to fyght agaynſte the common enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of it, let vs not therfore enuye one at an other, but let vs faithful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly helpe, aide, cheariſhe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte one an other in this pearyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous fyght. As for my parte, I am ready at all times, in thys ſo iuſt a warre againſt the ennemies of the grace of God, to retch forthe myne helpyng hande vnto all my fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full brethren, truſtinge that they wyll doe the like vnto me. Howe muche, I haue farthered nowe the cauſe of the truthe, lette the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye iudge. Onlye this ſhall be to deſire your honorable Lordſhyppe to accept this my rude labor, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che withall due ſubmiffion I offer vnto youre honoure, as vnto the
<pb facs="tcp:1437:7"/> Mecenas and patron of all godlye learninge and true religion, beſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching almighty God the authoure of al goodneſſe, to proſper al your godlye enterpriſes to his honoure and glorye, and to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth of this floryſhynge realme.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="summary">
            <pb facs="tcp:1437:8"/>
            <head>¶The argument of this preſent boke.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this diſputatyon or dyſcourſe of free wyll, we doe fyrſte ſpeake of it, as it was in man at hys fyrſt creation, and a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore his fall, where it is ſhewed, that the place that is aleadged out of the .xv. chapiter of Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, for the defence of free will, ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghte to be vnderſtanded of manne being in the eſtate of innocencye. For, then as S. Auguſtine dothe declare, hadde he free wyll, but by tranſgreſſing the lawe of God, he dyd loſe it. Whereby he did bothe bryng hym ſelf, and all hys poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity into a miſerable bondage, and thraldome. In the whiche we doe ſtill remaine vntyll the ſonne of God, by his holye ſpiritte hathe made vs free. For tyll then we are ſo preſſed downe with the ſeruy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of ſinne, and with the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyon
<pb facs="tcp:1437:8"/> of oure owne fleſhe, that we cannot as much as thincke a good thoughte, ye we runne headlonge into all kindes of ſinnes, beynge mooſte prompte and readye to doe what ſo euer the fleſhe and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil do moue, and tempte vs vnto. But after that we be once by the drawinge of the father, come vnto oure ſauioure Ieſu Chriſte, and haue fellowſhyp wyth hym, then do we by and throughe him, reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer that, which we loſt in Adam, but yet not ſo, that we be alwayes able to do the good, that we wold. As ſaint Paule him ſelfe dothe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrme, ſayinge:<note place="margin">Rom. vii.</note> I do not the good thing, which I wold, but the euel that I woulde not, that do I. To be ſhorte, after longe diſputation, and many obiections made by the aduerſaries, and ſubſtantially an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered by Gods word, and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities of the auncient fathers, it is in fine concluded that all the good that we do, commeth nether of our
<pb facs="tcp:1437:9"/> fre wyl nor of our owne ſtrength, but of the mercy and grace of god, who worcketh the ſame in vs by his holy ſpirite, and that all the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill that is in vs cometh of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil and of our ſelues. Laſte of all, mention is made of the lawe, and of the fulfilling of the ſame. Wher it is plainlye proued, that no man is able to fulfil the law with ſuch a perfection as God dothe requyre of vs, and yet that no vnrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe can be laid to god, although, he commaundeth thinges, that be impoſſible for vs to do. By y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way the righte vſe of the lawe, and the vtility and profit of it, is diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſetforthe, and by what meanes we are delyuered from the curſe of the ſame. And ſo an end.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:1437:9"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>A mooſte neceſſarye Treatiſe of free wil, not only againſt the papiſtes but alſo againſt the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſtes, whych in theſe our dais goe aboute to renue the deteſtable hereſyes of Pelagius, and of the Luciferians, which ſay and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that we be able by our owne naturall ſtrengthe to fulfyl the law and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes of God. ¶Made dialoge wiſe by Ihon Veron, in a manner worde by word, as he dyd ſet it forth in his lectures at Paules.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>I wil haue mercy on him, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e I wil ſhew mercye, and wyll haue compaſſion on him, on whome I wil haue compaſſion.</p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Romains. ix. Ex. xxxiii.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Iacob haue I loued, and Eſau haue I hated. <bibl>
                        <hi>Ro. ix. Mala. i.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <stage>
               <pb facs="tcp:1437:10"/>
               <hi>Albion. Philalethes. Eutrapelus. Dydimus.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LBION.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">In the boke whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the huntinge of purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory vnto deathe.</note>I thyncke, that it is not yet ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of the clock, ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore, I thinke it beſt, that according to the counſel, that our neyghbor Dydi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus gaue vs yeſterday, we do ſyt here a whyle tyl the feruent heate of the ſunne be ouerpaſte, and that we do talcke and common of thoſe thynges, that do yet ſomwhat tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble my conſcyence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>Ye may or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vs, as it pleaſeth you, and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, ſyth that ye be ſo ready al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to geue place vnto the tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the. And therfore, let vs hear what thoſe thynges be, that do yet trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble your conſcyence, that we may, as we haue done here to fore, my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter vnto you, the ſalue of Gods worde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>I am muche bounde
<pb facs="tcp:1437:10"/> to you, brother Philalethes, for the great kindneſſe that ye ſhew vnto me, beyng ſo ready at al tymes, to healpe and ſuccoure me in thys great perplexity of mynde, that I am in God, I truſt, who is the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of all goodnes, and who hath inclyned your hart vnto me, ſhal reward thys your paynfull labor that ye take about me.</p>
               <p>O moſte mercyfull and bountious father,<note place="margin">A thanks geuinge ioigned with a faithfull prayer.</note> geuinge thee moſte hartye thankes for theſe thy benefyttes, wherewith thou haſt ſo graciouſlie refreſhed vs, we do humbly beſeche thee, to ſende thy holy ſpyrit in to oure heartes, that we may in this our communycation and talke, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourth thy glorye onely, to the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter confuſion and ouerthrowe of al the ſhamefull enemyes of thy free mercye and grace.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRAPE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LVS.</speaker>
               <p>God of his goodneſſe vouche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to graunte vs all,<note place="margin">The ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of goddes. grace.</note> that we may ſo do. For, there be manye in the worlde, which are ſuche enemyes
<pb facs="tcp:1437:11"/> of the free mercy and grace of God,<note place="margin">The pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes.</note> that whoſoeuer doth accordinge to the ſcriptures, affyrme or ſay, that we are ſaued only by his free mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye and grace, they are moſt ready to perſecute them wyth fyer and ſwerde, as moſt pernicious and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable heretykes, and as vtter enemies of all truth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DIDYMVS.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Ana<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>baptiſtes and free wil men.</note>Ye ſhall not onely fynde of them amonge the papyſtes, but alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge them, that wyll be coump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted moſt perfect chriſtians, &amp; moſt earneſt fauourers of the goſpel.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>Where ſo euer they he found, my faythfull guydes dyd tel me, that we haue fre wil: whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che thing ye do all denye. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: I would fayne hear, what ye can ſay, concerning that matter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALEEHES.</speaker>
               <p>What doe they vnderſtand by fre wyll? For, they are wonte to ſpeake of it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and ſondry wayes. Some do by it vnderſtand one thyng, and ſome an other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1437:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>They tolde me,<note place="margin">What ſcole men vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande by fre wyll.</note> that by free wyll they do vnderſtande a certaine facultye or power, beynge in ſeperably in the will of manne, wherby he mighte do or leaue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done any maner of thinge, as wit and reaſon dyd thinke or iudge it expediente. For, ſaye they, manne by hys wit and reaſon dothe conſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, weyghe, and ponder a thynge, and dothe examyne and trye whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be good or not: and then by the vertue of hys free wyll, eyther he dothe it, or leaueth it vndone, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as it pleaſeth hym.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>What mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned they, thynke ye,<note place="margin">After the papiſtes iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t we are maſters of oure wyll.</note> by that defy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBI.</speaker>
               <p>As it appeareth both by that difynition, and alſo by other talke, that they hadde after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes, their meaninge was, that we are maſters of oure owne wyll and iudgement, and that therfore, we canne by oure owne ſtrengthe turne oure ſelues whiche waye we lyſte, that is to ſay, that we be able
<pb facs="tcp:1437:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> by our owne vertue to do good or euil,<note place="margin">how blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous popiſhe doctrine is concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning free wyll.</note> to ſaue or damne our ſelues.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRA.</speaker>
               <p>O what blaſphemye is this againſt God and his worde? If ye do well marke this defyniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ye ſhall eaſely perceiue, that it is rather the difynition of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane and heathenyſhe Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers than of Chriſten doctours. Ye maye well vnderſtande, that if this definition wer true, we ſhuld not neede to pray vnto God for his helpe &amp; aſſiſtaunce, nor to call vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him for his holy ſpirit. We ſhoulde haue no nede to ſaye: if it pleaſeth God we wil do this thing or that thing. Do thei not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bi their defi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> place ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſtede &amp; roume of god?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PH.</speaker>
               <p>If theſe faithful guids of yours, had any zeale to ſetforthe the grace of God, &amp; his free mercy &amp; goodneſſe, they wold haue geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an other definitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto free wil.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>AL.</speaker>
               <p>Which, I praye you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHI.</speaker>
               <p>They wold at leaſt haue geuen the defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition that ſ. Auguſtine doth vſe.
<pb facs="tcp:1437:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> Which is this: <hi>Liberum arbitrium,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The defy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nition of free wyll after Sainte Auguſti.</note> 
                  <hi>eſt facultas rationis et voluntatis, qua bonum eligitur gratia adſiſtente, malum vero ea deſiſtente.</hi> That is to ſaye: free wyll is a vertue or power of the reaſonne and wyll, whereby the good is choſen, when the grace of God dothe adſiſte, and the euill when it is awaye or is wythdra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen. The meaninge is:<note place="margin">The mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ninge of Auguſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes defy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition.</note> that by free wyll, if we haue the adſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce and healpe of the grace of God, we are able to chuſe that, whiche is good, but if the grace of God be awaye, or be withdra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen, we can no more but embrace that, whiche is euyll, and hurte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to oure owne ſoules.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DIDY.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion </seg>
                  </label> And is there none other definition of fre wyll?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <note place="margin">The ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of ſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tences. Li ii. ſenten. diſtin. xxv.</note>Yea verelye. For, the maſter of Sentences, dothe wryte, that it is not ſayed, that man hathe free wyll, becauſe that he is as able to thinke and doo good, as he is to thinke &amp; do euyll, but becauſe that
<pb facs="tcp:1437:13"/> he is not ſubiect vnto neceſſitye or compulſyon.<note place="margin">Lombar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus his meaning</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DyDIMVS.</speaker>
               <p>What ſhuld he mene by that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>Hys mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng is,<note place="margin">Schole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note> that the euyl, which man doth, he doth it frely, and wythout compulſion. And therefore, the ſchole men ſaye, that this fredome and libertye is not letted, thoughe we be wicked, and ſeruauntes of ſinne, and can no more but ſynne ſtil and offend. But truely this ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not be vnderſtanded of a man, that is regenerated or borne of newe. For, the holy ghoſt, that is in him dothe wythſtande the euil, that he would do. And likewiſe by this de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>finition or determinatyon of the maſter of ſentences, it myghte be ſaid, that a man, which is regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated or borne of newe hathe free will,<note place="margin">How it maye be ſaied that a man which is regenera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted hath free wyll Eccleſia. cus xv. chapi.</note> becauſe that the ſame lyttle good that he doth, he doth it frely, and frankly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>They dyd brynge in
<pb facs="tcp:1437:13"/> a place out of Eccleſiaſticus, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe called Ieſus the ſonne of Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rach, wher it is thus written: God made man from the beginning and lefte him in the hande of his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaill. He gaue him his commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes, and preceptes. If thou wylt obſerue the commaundemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and kepe acceptable faythful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for euer, they ſhall preſerue the. He hath ſet fyer and water be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore thee, reache oute thine hande vnto whiche thou wilte. Before manne is life and death, good and euyll, loke what him liketh, ſhalbe geuen him.<note place="margin">Epiſto. ad cteſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phontem</note> They did alſo aleadge many doctours, as Ierome againſt the Pelagians, where he ſayeth thus: In this doo we dyffer from brute beaſtes, that we haue bene created with free will.<note place="margin">Li. ii con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tra mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio. home ix. in gen Ei. xii. mora.</note> They did aleadge Tertulian, Chriſoſtome and Hilary. Which all do affirme that man hath ſuche free wyll, as they did declare vnto me afore.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>The place,
<pb facs="tcp:1437:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> that they aleadged out of Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticus, maketh nothinge for them. for,<note place="margin">how the place of Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticus ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght to be vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded.</note> it oughte to be vnderſtanded of man being in the fyrſt eſtate of his creation, and beynge in his origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall innocency and righteouſneſſe. And becauſe that it ſhall not bee thoughte, that I bringe any thing of mine owne heade, ye ſhall heare what Saynte Auguſtine ſayethe, whoſe wordes, are theſe: free wyll before the fall was an vprighte free wyll,<note place="margin">De ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tico<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nouo. ca. viii.</note> before whiche, fyer and water was layed of God, and the fyrſte manne dyd reatche hys hande to whyche he woulde, hee dyd choyſe fier, and forſoke wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. See the ryghteous iudge, the ſame, whiche manne beinge free dyd choyſe, he dyd receaue, he woulde haue euyll, and the ſame did folowe him.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Contra fortu. Diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>puta. xi.</note>And in an other place, theſe be alſo hys woordes: I ſaye that fre wyl was in that man, which
<pb facs="tcp:1437:14"/> was created fyrſt. For, he was ſo made, that nothinge coulde withſtande hys wyll, if he would haue kepte Goddes commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes but after that hee hadde ſynned throughe free wyll, hee dyd caſt vs all that come of hys ſtocke, into neceſſitye. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, he writeth in an other place,<note place="margin">In enche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid ad lau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ren. Ca. xxx. De ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer. ii.</note> that manne vſinge not well free wyll, did bothe loſe it &amp; him ſelf. Againe: It is true (ſayeth he) that manne when he was made did receaue greate ſtrength of free wyll, but he did loſe it through ſynne.</p>
               <p>Theſe autorityes of Sainte Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine doo ſufficientely declare, how the place that they aleaged oute of Eccleſiaſticus oughte to be vnderſtanded.</p>
               <p>For, there doubteleſſe, the wiſe manne dothe ſpeake of man, as he was firſt created in the eſtate of in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nocency and righteouſnes, and not
<pb facs="tcp:1437:15"/> as he was wyth his poſteritye af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hys fall,<note place="margin">De eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dogm. ca. xxxii.</note> whereby as Saynte Auguſtine ſaithe, all menne haue loſte theyr naturall poſſibilitye, or ableneſſe, and theyr naturall or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall innocencye. And ſo ought the doctoures, that they dyd bryng in, for them ſelues, to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtanded, for they do all ſpeake of manne as he was afore his fall. Whyche thynge appeareth to be moſte true by the ſaying of Saint Hierome,<note place="margin">Iero in xxiii. cap. Iere.</note> who wrytinge vppon Ieremy ſaithe plainly theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des: And therefore, the heretykes be wonte to promyſe felicity, and to open vnto ſinners the kingdom of heauen, ſaying: Thou maiſt fo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowe the maieſtye of God, and be without ſynne, ſyth that thou haſt receyued the power or ſtrength of free wyll, and the vnderſtandyng of the lawe, whereby thou arte a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble to obtayne what ſo euer thou wylte. And ſo the ſaide Heretykes do deceyue the poore, ſymple, and
<pb facs="tcp:1437:15"/> ignoraunt perſonnes, and ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly women, whyche beynge loden with ſinnes, are ledde to and froe with euerye winde of doctrine, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuynge by theyr flattery al them that geue eares vnto them. Heare ye ſee that ſaint Ierome dothe call them all Heretikes, that ſaye, that menne be able by theyr free wyll, to do bothe good and euyll. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uppon we maye well conclude, that in his Epiſtle ad Cteſiphon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>em,<note place="margin">Exiſto ad cteſiphon tem.</note> he dothe ſpeake of the fyrſte eſtate of manne, that he was in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hys tranſgreſſyon and fall. And as for Chriſoſtome, although he dothe exceade in extollynge the naturall ſtrengthe of manne,<note place="margin">hom. i. in aduen.</note> yet dothe he confeſſe plainelye, that euerye manne, is not onely of hys owne nature a ſynner, but alſo that he is ſynne altogether.</p>
               <p>Whereby he doth ouerthrow, what ſo euer, he dothe wryte or ſaye in anye other place, in the commendacyon of free wyll, and
<pb facs="tcp:1437:16"/> of oure natural ſtrengthe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRAPELVS.</speaker>
               <p>That muſt be mooſte true. For, if accordynge to his owne ſayinge, we be not only ſinners of our owne nature, but alſo ſynne all together, where is oure gaye payncted free wyll be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. viii.</note>Dothe not the truthe hym ſelfe ſaye, that euery man that ſinneth, is a ſeruaunte of ſynne? Againe, is it not wrytten that of whome ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer a manne is ouercome,<note place="margin">ii. Pet. ii</note> vnto the ſame he is in boundage? It ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth then by thys, that we are verye farre from that liberty and fredome, that they doe ſo muche boaſte of.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DYDIMVS.</speaker>
               <p>Wherefore did then theſe ancient fathers and wryters of the Catholike churche extoll ſo muche the free will and naturall ſtrengthe of manne?<note place="margin">Home. lii</note> For, Chriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, hath alwaies in his mouth: Let vs bring that, whiche is oure own, God wyl ſupply the reſidue.
<pb facs="tcp:1437:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> Where vnto Ierome doth agree, ſaying: <hi>Noſtrum eſt incipere,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dia. iii. con. Pela<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gianes.</note> 
                  <hi>dei au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem perficere: Noſtrum eſt, offerre quod poſſumus, illius implere quod non poſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</hi> That is to ſaye: It is our part for to begin, and it is Gods parte for to performe. It is our parte, to offer that, whiche we can, and it is his part to ſupply or fulfyll that, that we can not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>It is moſte playne,<note place="margin">Why the aunciant fathers ſpake ſo of fre wil that they dyd ſeme to alowe it.</note> that they did it to thys end, that they might driue awaye all ſlouggiſhneſſe from menne. Which thing they that came after did not perceiue. And therefore, they did attribute ſo muche to the free will and naturall ſtrength of man, that the fre mercy and grace of God was in a manner vtterlye forgotten.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DyDIMVS.</speaker>
               <p>Howe can it be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that they did tt onlye for that purpoſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>It is eaſy to be proued. For, if they ſhoulde
<pb facs="tcp:1437:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> meane as they write, they ſhoulde directly be againſt the plain ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and worde of God, and alſo againſt them ſelues. Fyrſt and foremoſt, the LORD him ſelfe ſaieth: I wyll hencefourth curſe the earth no more for mans ſake.<note place="margin">Gen. viii</note> For, the ymagination of mannes heart is euyll, euen from the very youth of him. And Moſes for to de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clare,<note place="margin">Deu. xxix</note> how vnable we be of oure ſelues to vnderſtande heauenlye thinges, doth ſaye plainlye theſe wordes: Ye haue ſeene all that the Lorde did before youre eyes in the lande of Egipte, vnto Pharao and vnto and all his ſeruaunts. Thine eies haue ſene theſe great tokens and wonders. And yet vnto this day, hath not the Lorde geuen you a harte, that vnderſtandeth, eies that ſee &amp; eares that heare.</p>
               <p>What could he ſaye more, excepte he ſhuld call vs blocks and ſtones? And in Ezechiel the Lorde ſayeth: A new heart,<note place="margin">Eze. xxvi.</note> wyl I geue you, and
<pb facs="tcp:1437:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> a newe ſpirit wyl I put in to you. As for that ſtony hearte, I wyll take it oute of youre bodye, and geue you a fleſhy hart. I will geue you my ſpirit amonge you, and cauſe you to walke in my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements, to kepe my lawes and to fulfyll them. This place onely doth ſufficientely teache vs, that excepte oure ſtony heartes be taken away from vs, and fleſſhy, that is to ſaye, obediente hartes geuen vs in ſtede of them, yea and a newe ſpirit put in to vs (whiche ſhoulde worke in vs an obedience towards the Lordes commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes) we are able to do nothing we can in no wyſe kepe the lawes of God, nor yet fulfyll them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRAPELVS.</speaker>
               <p>In dede theſe wordes are very playne. For, by them we do learne, that all that we haue of oure owne, muſt either be renewed, or taken away, afore that we canne do any thinge, that pertaine to oure ſaluation. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb facs="tcp:1437:18"/> any man may eaſlye perceaue, that the liberty and freedome that we haue to do well, is very ſmall, or rather nothing at all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LETHES.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. iii.</note>Be not theſe the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of Iohn zacharyes ſonne: A man can receaue nothinge, except it be geuen him from aboue? Wher doubtleſſe he ſpeaketh, not of the comon giftes of nature, but of the ſpeciall gyfte of the holye ghoſt. For, there dothe he complain; that his diſciples were neuer the better for all hys preachinges, wherein he had ſet fourthe Chriſt vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. As if he ſhoulde haue ſayed: I do ſee and perceaue, that woordes are nothinge auaileable for to teach and inſtructe menne in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlye thynges, excepte the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ghoſt, woorkynge inwarde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye dothe geue the vnderſtanding. Vnto thys dothe oure ſauyoure Ieſu Chriſte agree,<note place="margin">Iohn. vi.</note> when hee ſayethe: No manne canne come vnto me, excepte it be geuen him
<pb facs="tcp:1437:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> of my father. For this cauſe, when Peter hadde ſayed: Thou arte Chriſte the ſonne of the lyuinge God. This aunſwere dyd oure ſauioure Ieſus Chriſt make vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him agayne: bleſſed art thou Simon the ſonne of Ionas: For, fleſhe and bloude hath not opened that vnto thee,<note place="margin">Mat. xvi.</note> but my father that is in heauen.</p>
               <p>And in an other place: whoſoeuer (ſayeth he) dothe heare and learne of the father, cometh vnto me.<note place="margin">Iohn. vi.</note> But the bleſſed Apoſtell doth moſt ſtrongely heate downe the vayne pride of oure free wyll men, wher he writeth on this manner: The naturall man perceaueth nothing of the ſpirit of God.<note place="margin">i. Cor. ii.</note> Whereby he doth vnderſtande, that the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall man, which is not renewed in Chriſt, can not perceiue the things that be of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit of god. For, why they are but folyſhenes vnto him. And in his ſecond Epiſtel to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians, theſe be alſo his words:<note place="margin">ii. Cor. iii</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1437:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> Such truſt haue we through chriſt to God ward, not that we are ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient of our ſelues to thincke any thing, as it were of our ſelues, but our ableneſſe commeth of God. Nowe if we be not able to thynke a good thought, except God dothe put it in vs: howe muche more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able be we, ether to wil or to do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing that good is, or accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the ſight of God? But let vs graunt vnto you by way of diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and reaſoninge, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue no ſuch thing in the boke of God: what ſhall they winne by it? For, I am able to bring nowe, foure of the moſt principal doctors againſt theyr two.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DyDIMVS.</speaker>
               <p>Whiche are they, I beſeche you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILA.</speaker>
               <p>Fyrſte, the bleſſed mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr Saint Cyprian,<note place="margin">Li. de pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deſt. ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum ad bonifaciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Li. iiii. et alibi. cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prianus.</note> who is a moſt aunciente doctor, hathe lefte thys golden ſentence vnto vs by wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting: De nullo nobis gloriandum eſt, quia nihil noſtrum eſt, niſi vt
<pb facs="tcp:1437:19"/> homo apud ſe prorſus exinanitus, a deo totus pendere diſcat. That is to ſay: we oughte to boſte of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge: For, nothing is our owne, ſauing only that man being of no reputation with hym ſelfe, muſte learne to hange all to gether of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRA.</speaker>
               <p>As farre, as I doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, Saint Auguſtyne dothe many times rehearſe the ſame ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing of Cyprian.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILA.</speaker>
               <p>Ye ſay true. For, he ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth mention of it in hys booke of the Predeſtination of ſaintes, and in manye other places beſydes. But he hym ſelf doth wryte much after the ſame manner, when he ſayeth. Nemo ſe palpet,<note place="margin">Hom. in. Iohanne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> xlix.</note> de ſuo Sathanas eſt: id vnde beatus eſt, a deo tantum habet. Quid N. de tuo habes niſi peccatum?</p>
               <p>Tolle tibi peccatum quod tuum eſt. Nam iuſtitia deteſt. Whyche wee maye Englyſhe after thys ſorte.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1437:20"/>
               <p>Let no man flatter him felfe: for, of hys owne he is a very Sathan he hath that of God only, wherby he is bleſſed. For, what haſte thou of thyne owne but ſinne? Take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye ſynne from thee, whiche is thine owne: For, righteouſneſſe is of God. Ye ſee howe well he dothe ſetforthe manne in hys owne co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loures. But ye ſhall heare alſo what Gregory ſaith:<note place="margin">Grego. li moraliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. xxii. ca. x.</note> Sciunt ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti viri (ſayeth he) ſe poſt primi pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentis lapſum, de corruptibili ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe editos, et non virtute propria, ſed preueniente gratia ſuperna, ad meliora ſe vel vota, vel opera commutatos, et quicquid ſibi ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li ineſſe cognoſcunt de mortali pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pagine ſentiunt meritum. Quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid vero boni in ſe inſpiciunt, immortalis gratiae cognoſcunt do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</p>
               <p>That is to ſay: holy men do know that after the fall of the fyrſte fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they be borne of a corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſtocke, and that they be not by
<pb facs="tcp:1437:20"/> theyr owne vertue, but by the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernall grace, that dothe preuent them, turned vnto better deſyres or woorkes: and what euyl ſo euer they knowe to be in them ſelues, they feale that it is deſerued and come of theyr mortall kynde. But what good ſo euer they ſee to be in them ſelues, they acknowledge to be the gyft of the immortal grace. And for this gyfte that they haue receyued, they be debtoures vnto hym, whych by preuentyng them, dyd geue vnto theym, that they ſhoulde wyll that good thynge, whyche they woulde not, and by followinge did graunte that they ſhuld be able to do that good thing that they would.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRAPE.</speaker>
               <p>O that all faythfull Chriſtians,<note place="margin">A godlye wyſhe.</note> woulde haue alwayes this ſayinge of Gregorye before their eies. For, they learne there<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by, that they that be ſanctifyed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holi goſt, as thei do acknowledge that after the fal of the fyrſte man,
<pb facs="tcp:1437:21"/> they are bothe conceiued and born in ſinne, ſo do they vnfainedly con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſe, that all the good mynde and will, that they haue to doe thoſe woorkes, that God dothe requyre of vs, commeth not of them ſelues, nor of theyr owne naturall vertue and ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, but of the mere grace and goodneſſe of God, wherewith he dothe preuent them, that they maye haue ſuche a good wyll and mynde to do good, and wherwyth he, as followinge, he dothe healpe and adſiſt them, that they maye be able to fulfill and perfourme that good thinge, that he hathe moued them to will.</p>
               <p>Againe, the euil that they feele to be in them ſelues, they doe not abſcribe it vnto their creation, nor yet to theyr creatoure and maker, but to theyr mortall generatyon, and corrupted nature: but all the goodneſſe that they perceiue to be in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, they attribute it not vnto their natural vertue &amp; ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth
<pb facs="tcp:1437:21"/> but vnto the grace and goodneſſe of God, withoute whiche we can not as muche, as thincke a good thoughte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILA.</speaker>
               <p>And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, Bernarde doth write verye well when he ſayeth on this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: Quid igitur? Hoc ergo totum liberi arbitrii opus,<note place="margin">In tracta tu de gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tia &amp; libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trio.</note> hoc ſolum eiꝰ eſt meritum quod conſentit? Eſt prorſus. Non quidem quod velcon fenſus, in quo omne meritum con ſiſtit, ab ipſo ſit: cum nec cogitare, (quod minus eſt quam conſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tire) a liquid a nobis, quaſi ex nobis ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficientes ſimus. Verba ſunt non mea, ſed Apoſtoli, qui omne, quod bonum eſſe poteſt, id eſt cogitare, et velle &amp; perficere, pro bona vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntate, attribuit deo, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuo arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trio. That is to ſay: what then? Is this therfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole work of fre wyll? Is this the only merit of it, that it dothe conſente, and agree? Truly it is. Not that the conſent, wherin all the merit doth conſiſt, doth come or is of it: ſyth that we
<pb facs="tcp:1437:22"/> be not of our ſelues, as of our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues able to thinke any thing, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is leſſe than to conſent or agre. Theeſe be not my wordes, but the wordes of the Apoſtle, which doth attribute vnto God, and not vnto hys free wyll, all that be good, that is to ſaye: to thyncke, and to wyll, and to perfourme accordyng to his good wyll and pleaſure.</p>
               <p>Here do we learne that Bernard doth adſcribe al thynges vnto god, and nothing to fre wil: wherin he doth agree with S. Auguſtin,<note place="margin">Li. de ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſi. dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma. xxvii</note> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge: God dothe ſo woorke in the hartes of men, and in the fre wyll it ſelf, that euerye good thoughte, godly counſel, and al good motion of the wil or minde is of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiectiō </seg>
                  </label> My faithfull guydes did tel me, that theſe be S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines wordes: who of vs all wyll ſay that throughe the ſinne of the fyrſt manne, fre wyll is pearyſhed from mankinde? It appeareth by thys, that notwithſtandynge the
<pb facs="tcp:1437:22"/> fall of the fyrſt man, we haue free wil ſtil.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DYDIMVS.</speaker>
               <p>Yea I doe remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that theſe woordes are alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged out of S. Auguſtin: Let no man be ſlack and ſlouthful to ſerue God, nor truſt ſo vppon grace,<note place="margin">Li. iii. hy pogno co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tra Pela.</note> as though God ſhuld not require the workes of his fre will: yea rather, let him ſhonne euill and do good. No man can deny but that theeſe be S. Auguſtines wordes. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he doth plainly declare, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> God doth require the workes of our fre wil. Which thing, he wold not do, except we had it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHI.</speaker>
               <p>It is a won<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der to ſe howe craftye the deuil is, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label> both in wraſting of the ſcriptures, &amp; alſo in peruerting of thancient fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers. In the firſte ſentence, that oure brother Albion dyd aleage,<note place="margin">The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils ſophi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtrie.</note> they do bring but a ſmal piece god wot. For, al that doth declare moſt plainelye the righte meanynge of Saint Auguſtin, the ſame do they mooſte craftely leaue of.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1437:23"/>
               <p>And becauſe no man ſhal thincke, that I goe about to ſclander them, ye ſhall heare al the hole ſentence of that auncient doctour,<note place="margin">The whole ſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tence of Auguſt.</note> which is this: who of vs wil ſay, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> through the ſinne of the firſt man, fre wyll is peariſhed from mankind? True<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, the fredome is peariſhed throu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghe ſinne: but the ſame that was in Paradiſe, to haue ful or perfect righteouſneſſe with immortality: Therefore mannes nature hathe neade of the grace of God, as oure ſauioure Ieſus Chriſte doth teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy, ſaying: If the ſonne of god doth deliuer you, then are ye free in deede, to liue wel and iuſtly. For, free wyll is not ſo pearyſhed vnto ſinners, but that they ſinne throu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghe it, ſpecially al thoſe, that ſinne wyth pleaſure, and throughe the loue that they haue vnto ſynne, whyche they do deſire, and whiche pleaſeth them.<note place="margin">What thinges are to be noted in ſaint Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtines wordes.</note> Marke well theeſe woordes. Fyrſt, he ſaithe that the ſame fredome is pearyſhed &amp; gon,
<pb facs="tcp:1437:23"/> whiche was in paradiſe, to haue perfecte righteouſneſſe with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality: meaninge therby, that wheras man had in Paradiſe free liberty to purchaſe vnto hym ſelf, a full and perfecte righteouſneſſe with immortality, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame is now peariſhed and lofte, throughe hys diſobedience and fall. Secondlye, he ſayth, that free wil is not ſo pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed vnto ſinners, but that they ſynne through it, ſpecially al thoſe that ſinne with pleaſure, whereby he doth vnderſtand, that for to doe frely and frankly the thynge that is good, we haue nead of the grace of God, and that the ſame manne which hath not the holy goſte, and which is not truelye regenerated, doth frely, and wythout compulſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſerue vnto ſinne, in ſo muche that he ſeemeth not to be the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt of ſinne, becauſe that the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel that he doth, he dothe it volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily, freelye and francklye. Who doth not ſee nowe, that S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine
<pb facs="tcp:1437:24"/> ſpeaketh nothinge of ſuche a free wyll, as your faithful guides do moſt ſhamefully goe aboute to maintaine and vphold. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in an other place, he wryteth on this manner: whye dare miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and wretched men be proud,<note place="margin">Li. de ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritu et li. tera. ca. xxx.</note> or boaſte theym ſelues either of fre wyll, afore that they be deliuered, or of theyr owne ſtrengthe, if they be already deliuered? And doe not marcke that in the verye name of free will, libertye or fredome is ſignifyed.</p>
               <p>But where the ſpiryte of the LORDE is, there is freedome and libertye: Therefore, if they be ſeruauntes of ſinne: whye do they boaſte theym ſelues of free wyll? For, of whome ſo euer anye manne is ouercome, to hym is hee delyuered to bee hys bounde manne.</p>
               <p>And if they be delyuered, whye doe they boaſte theym ſelues as of theyr owne woorke? Are they ſo
<pb facs="tcp:1437:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> free, that they refuſe to be the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes of him: that ſaythe:<note place="margin">Iohn. xv.</note> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute me ye canne doe nothynge? And in his booke, whyche he dyd wryte of grace and free wyl, theſe be hys woordes: Oure wyll is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes free,<note place="margin">capi. xv.</note> but it is not alwayes good. For, eyther it is free from righteouſneſſe, when it ſerueth vnto ſynne, and then it is euyl, or it is free from ſynne, when it ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vnto righteouſneſſe, and then it is good.</p>
               <p>Whyche ſentence he doth both repeate, and alſo expound in hys other woorkes, ſayinge playnely,<note place="margin">Li. ad bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifa. cap. ii.</note> that manne is made free from ryghteouſneſſe, by hys owne free wyll, but that he canne not bee made free from ſynne, ſauyng on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye by the grace of oure Sauy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oure.</p>
               <p>Is not thys, I praye you, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryde and laughe to ſcorne, the vayne Tytle and name of Free wil?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1437:25"/>
               <speaker>DYDIMVS.</speaker>
               <p>Yet, in the ſayinge that I haue aledged, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiectiō </seg>
                  </label> he dothe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrme, and ſay, that God dothe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyre the workes of our free wyll, whych can not be vnderſtanded of ſynne. For, God doth vtterlye for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid it. Whereby I maye conclude, that oure wyll is free to doe good woorkes, els God woulde not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyre the workes of our fre wyll.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>When I haue rehearſed vnto you the hole ſentence, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label> as it lyeth wrytten in S. Auguſtin, then iudge ye your ſelf, whether they do not followe the ſteppes of theyr greate graundfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the deuell, in peruerting both the ſcryptures, and alſo the auncy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent fathers. And that ye maye be the ſurer of it, ye ſhall haue it fyrſt in Latin, and then afterwardes in Englyſhe.<note place="margin">Augu. li. contra pe lagi. hypo ge.</note> The Latin is this: Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo ſit remiſſus et ſegnis ad ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendum deo, nec ſic de gratia con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidat, tanque deus liberi arbitrit eiꝰ, quod per morte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> filii ſui repara<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uit,
<pb facs="tcp:1437:25"/> et ſibi preparauit, opera non requirat, imo declinet a malo et fa ciat bonum. That is to ſay: Lette no man be ſlacke and ſlouthfull to ſerue God, nor truſte ſo vppon grace, as though God ſhoulde not requyre the woorckes of that free wyll, whych he hath both reſtored and prepared vnto hym ſelf by the death of his ſonne. Yea rather: let hym flye from euyll and do good.<note place="margin">What free wyll ſaint Au. doth vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtand.</note> Any child may eaſely perceiue and vnderſtand of what fre wil Saint Auguſtine doth ſpeake there: euen of that ſame free will whiche God hath alreadye reſtored agayne and prepared vnto him ſelf, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of hys ſonne Ieſu Chriſt, who on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye is able to deliuer vs from the ſeruitude and bondage of ſynne, and by his holye ſpirit to make vs to do frely thoſe woorkes, whyche GOD hathe prepared for vs, to walcke in. Therefore in an other place, he ſaith plainlye theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. Thinckinge diligentlye and
<pb facs="tcp:1437:26"/> faythfully on theſe and other lyke thinges, let vs not conſent or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree vnto them,<note place="margin">Idem lib. l. home. xiiii.</note> which extollinge free wyll vnto pride, do rather go aboute, to caſt it downe than to ſet it vp. But let vs conſyder with all humilitye and lowlyneſſe the ſayinge of the Apoſtell, where he ſayeth: It is God that worketh in vs both to wyl and alſo to worke: and ſo geue thankes vnto oure Lorde and ſauioure, whych with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute any merytes goynge before, dyd heale vs beynge wounded, and dyd reconſyle vs beynge ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes, dyd delyuer vs from cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyuitye, dyd bryng vs from darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vnto lyghte, and from death dyd call vs vnto life againe:</p>
               <p>And confeſſyng humbly our infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitye and weakeneſſe, let vs call vpon his mercy, that ſyth he hath preuented vs (accordinge to the Pſalmiſtes ſaying) with his grace he vouchaf not only to kepe in vs, but alſo to augmente and encreaſe
<pb facs="tcp:1437:26"/> his gyftes or rather his benefites, whiche he dyd vouchaf to geue vs. Theſe words ar ſo plain, that any childe is able to vnderſtand them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>They did yet aledge an other place oute of his treatiſe, vpon the firſt epiſtel of Iohn. The wordes are theſe: And euery man that hath this hope in him, pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth him ſelfe, euen as he is pure. Se how he hath not take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away fre wyll, in ſo much that he did ſay: he purgeth him ſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THES.</speaker>
               <p>The ſame fraude and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceate ſhal ye fynde in the aleaging of this place, that ye haue founde alredy in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aboue reherced autory<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties. For, it foloweth immediatly after who doth purge vs but god? But God dothe not pourge thee agaynſte thy wyll. Therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that thou doſte ioygne thy good wyll vnto god, thou purgeſt thy ſelfe. Thou purgeſt thy ſelfe, not of thy ſelfe, but of hym that cometh to dwell in thee.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1437:27"/>
               <p>yet becauſe that thou doſte there ſomewhat willinglye, therfore is ſome thinge attributed vnto thee: that thou maiſt ſaye, as it is wryt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the xxvi. Pſalme. Thou art my healper, do not forſake me. If thou ſayeſt: thou arte my healper, thou doſt ſomwhat, for if thou doſt nothing, how dothe he helpe thee. Fyrſt, and foremoſt we may eaſely perceiue by the texte that he goeth vpon,<note place="margin">Here. S. Auguſt. ſpeaketh of the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that is al redy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued.</note> that he dothe ſpeake of hym that is already renewed in Chriſt: els how coulde he haue anye hope of life euerlaſtinge? And for thys cauſe he ſayth by and by: who doth purge vs but God? But it is not vnknowen vnto you, that GOD doth only pourge vs through faith in our ſauiour Ieſu Chriſt, which faith, is the mother of hope. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore, er we can haue this hoope of lyfe euerlaſtinge, whiche the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Euangeliſt Saint Ihon dothe ſpeake of there, we muſte be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged throughe faythe. It is plaine
<pb facs="tcp:1437:27"/> then, that ther he ſpeaketh of him, that is already made a newe crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in Chriſte, by whoſe ſpirite, which commeth to dwel in vs, we are purged and made cleane, and not of our ſelues.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>What meaneth he then, when he ſaythe: <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion </seg>
                  </label> that GOD purgeth no manne agaynſte hys wyll? where vppon he dothe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that we do pourge oure ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, becauſe that we ioygne oure good will vnto God. And a lyttle after it followeth: if thou ſayſte, thou art my helper, then thou doſt ſomewhat: For, if thou doſte no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing howe canne he healpe thee? Here do we learne, as far as I can gather by his wordes. Firſte, that we muſt bryng our good wyll vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God: for, he wil ſaue no man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his will. Secondly, that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we do ſomewhat, we can not ſay truelye, that God is oure hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DIDYMVS.</speaker>
               <p>Truelye that was
<pb facs="tcp:1437:28"/> wel marcked of you, brother Albi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I thought mi ſelf to haue made the ſame obiection, excepte ye had preuented me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label> I do not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny but that we muſte brynge oure good will vnto God. But of whom haue we this good wil? haue we it of oure ſelues, thincke ye? Heare what S. Paule ſaythe: It is God, that worketh in you,<note place="margin">Phi. ii.</note> both the wil, and alſo the dede, euen of his own good will. Where (as Saint Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine doth wryte) he doth ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly declare,<note place="margin">Ad ſimpli ci. li. i. Queſti. xi</note> that it is God that wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth in vs, the good wil. For, if we ſhould aſke, whether the good wil be a gyfte of GOD or not, it is maruayle if any man dareth ſay naye.</p>
               <p>Where vnto Fulgentius dothe agree, ſayinge: Euerye good work then, whyche we doe woorke in god, the ſame dothe god woorke in vs. For, all thinges are of him,
<pb facs="tcp:1437:28"/> throughe hym, and in hym. Both oure good wyll then, and alſo oure good workes be of hym.</p>
               <p>Whyche thynge, the doctour of the gentyles dothe affyrm with theſe wordes.</p>
               <p>It is God that woorketh in vs, bothe the wyll and the deede, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of hys good wyll and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. Ye ſee then of whome we haue thys good wil, that we muſt brynge vnto God, euen of hym ſelfe and not of vs.</p>
               <p>For, it is he and none other that dothe worke it in vs, by hys holye ſpirit.</p>
               <p>And therefore, where he ſayeth: that GOD ſaueth or purgeth no manne agaynſte hys wil, the ſame is mooſte true:<note place="margin">Home. ix. Ezechie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</note> but as Gregorye wryteth, he dothe preuente vs, wyth his grace that we maye be willinge, and with his healpynge hand he dothe followe vs, leaſt we ſhuld will in vaine. And therefore
<pb facs="tcp:1437:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> the churche prayeth ſayinge: Et noſtras rebelles ad te compelle vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntates. That is to ſay: And com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell or dryue oure rebellious wyls vnto thee. Beholde (ſayeth he) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte oure rebellious wyll be dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto God, it is not healed. So ſaith our ſauiour: No man is able to come vnto me, excepte my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth drawe him. We are dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen againſt our wils, but we are lead willinglye or with our wils. It appeareath by this,<note place="margin">How of vn wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lnge we are made willing.</note> that of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willinge perſons, we muſt, by the inwarde drawing of our heauenly father, be made wylling: els oure wils ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be healed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their natu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ral rebelliouſneſſe, which we haue of oure fyrſte parents Adam and Eue. Thus then we maye righte well ſay, that God ſaueth no man againſt his wyll: For, why? He maketh them all wyllinge afore, whome he dothe ſaue.<note place="margin">How this ought to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanded, that God ſaueth no man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his wyll.</note> And whom he made wyllinge, them dothe he alſo healpe, aide, and adſiſt, that
<pb facs="tcp:1437:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> they maye doo the thinge, that he hathe made them wyllinge to do. And ſo maye we affyrme boldely, that God is oure healper. becauſe that beinge throughlye regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or renewed in Chriſte, we do through the aſſiſtaunce and helpe of his holy ſpirit, worke with his grace.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRAPELVS.</speaker>
               <p>Nowe maye ye perceaue and ſee,<note place="margin">The faith fullneſſe that the papiſtes do vſe in aleaging the aunci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ent wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</note> what truth and faithfulneſſe, youre ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall gentyll men do vſe, in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadginge the olde writers of the auncient Catholyke churche. And that all that they go aboute, is by hooke and by crooke, to bringe men, from the true and right vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandinge of of Goddes worde: and to plucke them from the truſt, that they oughte to haue in the meare mercye and goodneſſe of God, and in his gratuite and free grace, in to a vayne confidence of their own natural vertu &amp; ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth. I woulde wyſhe, that at the leaſt they woulde alwayes haue before
<pb facs="tcp:1437:30" rendition="simple:additions"/> theyr eies, this goodly ſayinge of Eucherius biſhop of Lions: Chriſt ſaith he, is the tre of life, who ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer doth retch forth his hand vnto him, ſhal liue: but free will, is the tre of knowledge of good and euil: whoſoeuer forſaking the grace of God, wyll taſte of it, ſhall dye the death.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>Now wyl I tell you, what obiections I made agaynſte them. Fyrſt, I dyd aſke them why Ieremy did ſaye:<note place="margin">Iere. x.</note> Nowe I knowe, O Lorde, that it is not in mannes power, to order hys own wayes, or to rule hys owne ſteppes and goinges?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILA.</speaker>
               <p>Ye did go oute of youre matter. For, your communication was of heauenlye and ſpyrituall thinges, that is to ſaye, of the knowledge of God, and of his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed will, and whether we can rule oure ſelues accordynge vnto it. Whiche to doe, it lyeth not in the power or fre wil of man. But ther
<pb facs="tcp:1437:30"/> Ieremye dothe ſpeake of earthlye thinges, and which do pertain vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this preſent life. In deede, God hath yet left in man a certaine na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural light, wherby he may know what is good for this preſente lyfe of the bodye and for the gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his houſe,<note place="margin">Nothing can be broughte to paſſe by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrye of man with out the helpe of God. Pro. xvi.</note> but yet nothing can be bring to paſſe, wythout the ayde and healpe of God. So muſte the ſaying of the wyſe manne be vnderſtanded, where he ſaythe: A man deuiſeth in hys hart, but the Lord ordreth hys goynges. Wher vnto the common Prouerbe dothe agre, that is to ſay: Man doth pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, but God dothe diſpoſe. How be it, I woulde fayne knowe, what aunſwere, they made vnto you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>They dyd aunſwere me, that in deede manne was not able manye tymes to bringe that thynge to paſſe, that he woulde withoute the grace of God: &amp; that it lyeth not in the power of man
<pb facs="tcp:1437:31"/> to walke vprightly in the waye of righteouſneſſe without thaſſiſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and healpe of the holy ghoſte. And for the probation of it, they dyd bryng in certayne places, whiche ye haue aleadged alreadi, as theſe: A man can receaue nothing at all,<note place="margin">Iohn. iii.</note> except it be geuen hym fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue. Again:<note place="margin">ii. Cor. iii</note> we are not able of our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to thinke a good thought, but all our ableneſſe commeth of God. Alſo the ſaying of Sainte Iames,<note place="margin">Iam. i.</note> where he ſayeth: Euery good gift and euery perfect gifte is from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, and cometh downe from the father of light.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRA.</speaker>
               <p>I chaunced once to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon with a great doctor of diuinity who did affirme, that it dyd lye in our power to receyue the grace of God when it is offred vnto vs, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a great bragge, that he was able to proue it by manifeſt textes of the ſcripture. Then dyd I aſke the gentle manne whether it was not a good gift to receiue the grace
<pb facs="tcp:1437:31" rendition="simple:additions"/> of God, when it is offred? whyche thinge he did graunte by and by. Then did I make mine argument after this manner: Euerye good gift is from aboue, and commeth downe from the father of lyghte. But to receiue the grace of GOD when it is offred, is a good gyfte, ergo it commeth of God, that we do receyue hys grace, and not of our ſelues.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DYDIMVS.</speaker>
               <p>What anſwer did he make?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRA.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall Aunſwer of a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toure.</note>What anſwer he made me? I warrante you, a doctor lyke aunſwer. For, by and by he tooke hys gloues from vnder his girdle, and did caſt them vnto me, ſaying: Loe, I geue you theſe gloues, bee they not yours, when I haue geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you them? can it be ſaid, that they be mine ſtil?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILA.</speaker>
               <p>That was aunſweared like a doctoure. But go on ſtil bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Albion, I praye you dyd they aleadge any more?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1437:32"/>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>Yes. For, they dyd aleadge Gregory, who wrytinge vpon theſe woordes of the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt:<note place="margin">Gregori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us in pſal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mos.</note> My ſoule thyrſteth for thee in a barren and dry lande, where no water is: ſaith plainly theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des: Sith that fre wyll hathe bene corrupted in our fyrſte father, we are not able to wyl a good thyng, excepte we be healped wyth the grace of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>I knew ryghte well, that youre faythfull guydes, ſhoulde be fayn at length to crye peccaui, and to recante their dyuelyſhe and erroneous o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinyon.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the truth are againſt them ſelues.</note>For, if ye marcke well the defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, that they gaue vnto free wyll: ye ſhall fynde, that they dyd attrybute nothynge at all vnto the grace of God, yea no mention at all, was made of it. Ye ſe nowe that they ſaye agaynſt theyr own ſelues: wherein, they doe ſhewe
<pb facs="tcp:1437:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> theyr ignorance and beaſtiſhneſſe. They hadde ſpoken ſo largelye wythoute the boke, that they wer fayne to goe backe, and to vnſaye agayne that whych they had ſayde afore. But vppon this texte of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remy I myghte make myne argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente after thys manner: If man canne not wythoute the healpe of God,<note place="margin">A minori ad maius</note> brynge earthlye thynges to paſſe: howe muche leſſe ſhall he be able wythoute the grace of God, to come to the knowledge of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly thinges?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRAPE.</speaker>
               <p>Herein may we ſee the beaſtiſhneſſe of theſe bragging marchauntes of the cleargy. For, they do aſſone aleadge that, why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che maketh agaynſte theym, as that whyche ſeemeth to make for theym. For, if all thinges be well conſydered and marcked, the laſte authorities of the ſcripture, which they dyd aledge wyth the ſayinge of Gregory, doe make for vs all together.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1437:33"/>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>I doe confeſſe that it ſo. Howe be it, they alwayes har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped vpon this ſtringe, that manne hath free wil, and that ſuch ſenten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces and ſayinges do not take awai fre wil from vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILA.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">It is hard to take ought fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a naked man.</note>I know well ynoughe, that ſuch ſayinges can not take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way free wil from vs. For whye? we haue it not. And howe coulde that thynge be, taken awaye from vs, that we haue not? How ſo euer the matter goeth, ſuche ſentences do plainly declare, that man hath not ſuch fre wil, as they do mooſte lyingly affyrme.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>Therefore, I aſked them, whye oure ſauioure Ieſus Chriſt did ſaye: No man commeth vnto me,<note place="margin">Iohn. vi.</note> excepte my father dothe drawe him. For, it appeareth by theeſe wordes, that man hathe no fre wyl at al to do wel.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILA.</speaker>
               <p>What coulde they ſay to you againe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>They aleadged Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoſtome
<pb facs="tcp:1437:33"/> againſt me, wher he wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in this maner. The Maniche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans did go aboute to proue by this place, that we are able to do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge of oure owne ſelues: But they do not vnderſtande it well. For, by this ſayinge free wyll is not abolyſhed and put downe, but it is ſhewed and declared, that it hath alwayes neede of the healpe of God, and that God draweth no man againſt his wyll, but ſuch, as do, to the vttermoſt of their power endeuour them ſelues to come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him. And in an other place he ſayeth,<note place="margin">Home de conuer Pauli.</note> that God compelleth no manne to come vnto him againſt his wyll: but that he doth drawe them, that be wyllinge or that retche theyr handes vnto hym, for to be drawen of him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">How the ſaying of Chriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght to be taken.</note>The expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition and ſayinge of Chriſoſtome is partely true. For, I do graunt that God ſhall neuer ſaue them, that be obſtinate in their wycked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:1437:34" rendition="simple:additions"/> or that do obſtinately perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and continue in their vnbelief. To be ſhorte, I do confeſſe, that God wyll ſaue no man, excepte he doth conſente and agree firſt, and haue a wyll to be ſaued. But in this doth lye all the matter, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we haue thys wyll of oure ſelues or not. But we haue alre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye ſufficientlye proued bothe by the ſcriptures, and alſo by many autorities of the auncient fathers, that it is God onely that worketh in vs bothe the wyll,<note place="margin">Phi. ii.</note> and alſo the dede, accordinge to his good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. We muſt then vnderſtand, that God ſaueth no man that is vnwyllinge to be ſaued, or that doth withſtand and reſiſt alwaies his bleſſed wyll and pleaſure: but afore that he ſaueth any man, he maketh that ſame manne by his grace, to conſente and agree vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his bleſſed wyll and pleaſure: yea, he doth reatch fourth his hand vnto him, for ſo plucke him vp.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1437:34"/>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>They did ſaye vnto me in dede, that by the ſame dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winge,<note place="margin">Marke the vnſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blenes of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes of God.</note> we muſt vnderſtande the grace of God whiche dothe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent vs: or his inwarde admony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and callinge, wherby we are moued to do good, and to be obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diente vnto the lawe and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALE.</speaker>
               <p>I knewe righte well that they ſhoulde be fayne at length maugry their ſmothe ſhaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faces to attribute al vnto the grace of God, wherby he doth moue, ſtyr vp, and wake out of ſlepe the wil of man, geuinge it ſtrength to riſe vp, and to come vnto him, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by alſo he dothe reuele and open vnto him, the miſerye and wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chedneſſe, that he was in, and whyche was hydden from hym, and whereby he dothe ſtrengthen hym to walke in hys lawes and commaundementes, and to doe the thynge that is acceptable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hym.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1437:35"/>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>I did alſo, as occaſion gaue me, aleadge vnto them this ſayinge of Paule: I knowe that in me (that is to ſaye,<note place="margin">Ro. vii.</note> in my fleſhe) dwelleth no good thinge. To wyl is preſente wyth me but to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourme that, which is good, I find not. For, the good that I wyll, do I not, but the euyll, whiche I wyll not that do I.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHI.</speaker>
               <p>I woulde fayne heare what aunſwer they made vnto you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>They did by and by brynge in Chriſoſtome,<note place="margin">An obiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion oute of Chriſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtom.</note> who ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding this place, doth ſay that by theſe wordes the Apoſtell doth not take awaye free wyll, nor yet bring in any neceſſity or conpulſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For els in ſtede that he did ſay, <hi>nolo,</hi> I wil not, he ſhuld haue ſayed <hi>cogor,</hi> I am conſtreygned. Which thinge he did not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHI.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Aunſwer</note>If the expoſition of Chriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome wer true, then muſt we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that. S. Paul did voluntarely &amp; of his free wyl y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing that was
<pb facs="tcp:1437:35"/> euil, and that he did willinglye, &amp; of a ſette minde forſake the good that he mighte haue done. But to ſay ſo, were to blaſpheme, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye the Apoſtle, but alſo the holye ghoſt, that was in hym. For, who would ſay, that after Saint Paule was once conuerted and renewed in Chriſt, he did ſinne voluntare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, or that he did for the nonce, and of a ſet mind, forſake the good thyng, that he myghte haue done? I aſke you: if ye ſhoulde doe that thyng, which ye wold not do, wer it not by compulſion, that ye ſhuld do it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>Yes verely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALE.</speaker>
               <p>Know ye then,<note place="margin">A gloſſe of Orle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. Chriſoſt. maketh no dyffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce betwixte the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall man and the man that is regene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rated.</note> that thys is a gloſſe of Orleans, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che deſtroyeth the text. For, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome maketh there no dyffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, betwyxt the carnal manne, and the manne that is renewed in Chriſte.</p>
               <p>Where as Saynte Paule dothe ſpeake there of the manne that is
<pb facs="tcp:1437:36"/> regenerated or borne of new, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che thing he doth vnder hys owne perſon, that we might be the ſurer that it is ſo. For, ye ſhal vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that as the carnal and fleſhly men do geue them ſelues frely to be the bounde ſeruauntes of ſynne, ſo in them that be renewed in Chriſte,<note place="margin">In them that are borne of new ther is a conty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nuall bat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taile be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the ſpirit and the fleſh.</note> and made newe creatures by hys holy ſpirit, there is alwayes a con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinuall batayle betwixt the ſpirite and the fleſhe, ſo that the euil that they do, they do it, being ouercom by the fleſh, which dothe alwayes luſt againſt the ſpirite: And if they leaue anye good thinge vndone, whych they wolde do, it is becauſe that the rebelliouſnes of the fleſhe wyll not let them, nor yet ſuffer them to do it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>They ſaid moreouer that if I woulde well marcke,<note place="margin">The fonde ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iection of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes.</note> to what purpoſe, Sainte Paule dyd ſpeake that, wayghinge the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des that go before, and the wordes that come after, I ſhoulde fynde,
<pb facs="tcp:1437:36"/> that Saint Paul doth ſpeke there of the ſenſuality of man, which is alwaies repugnant vnto reaſon, becauſe of oure corrupted nature, and not of fre wyl. For, he ſaythe by and by after: It is not I that do it, but ſinne that dwelleth in me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Aunſwer</note>Althoughe this be the diſtinccion of a Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pher, going about to defend mans ſtrength, and to proue that reaſon is perfect in hym, I meane, in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet if ye wil marke diligentlye the woordes and ſayinges of youre faythfull guydes, ye ſhal find that there was a certayne repugnance in Saynt Paule.</p>
               <p>It followeth then, that there was in hym no ſuche Free wyll, as they doe boaſte of. For, it was not the wyll of Saynte Paule, that dyd the ſame euyll, but hys ſenſuality.</p>
               <p>Therefore, the wyll oughte to haue reſyſted this ſenſualitye, if it be ſo ſtronge, that it is able to doe
<pb facs="tcp:1437:37"/> what ſoeuer it wil. Neuertheleſſe S. Paule, afore he ſpake thus, had ſayd: we know that the law is ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, but I am carnall, ſold vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſynne. Ye ſe how he ſayth. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go, I. Whereby he dothe vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand all that was in hym of hys corrupted nature, as is both mans reaſon and wyll: he ſaythe not my ſenſuality is ſold vnder ſin, but he ſaith: I am carnal &amp; ſold vnder ſin. And afterwardes he called all hys corrupted nature, ſynne, ſayinge: It is not I that do it, but ſin that dwelleth in me: vnderſtanding by ſinne, the natural corruption that was in him. The holye ſcrypture doth put no difference betwixt ſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſuality and reaſon,<note place="margin">In thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that pertain to ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſualitye.</note> makinge reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more perfect than the ſenſuality is in heauenlye thinges, or in thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that pertayne to ſaluation.</p>
               <p>For, man hym ſelf beynge not yet renewed, is altogether fleſhly and carnall, he is nothinge els, I ſaye, but ſenſuality. Therfore, brother
<pb facs="tcp:1437:37" rendition="simple:additions"/> Albion, beware of ſuch doctours, as your bragging faithfull guides be, whiche haue lieuer to followe heatheniſh philoſophers, than the ſpirit of God. For, ſuch doctoures do all that they can to caſte manne headlong into hell, being like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſerpent, whyche ſayde vnto Eue: ye ſhall be as God,<note place="margin">gene. iii.</note> knowing bothe good and euell. For, to ſette man vppon his fre wyl, is to ſette man vppon a reede, and vpon va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing ſmoke.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DYDIMVS.</speaker>
               <p>What if I ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon thus with you? <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiectiō </seg>
                  </label> Eyther ſynne is of neceſſity, or it lieth in the wil and power of man: If it be of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity: that is to ſaye, if a man by neceſſitye is dryuen to it, whye ſhould he be puniſhed for it. Again if it lieth in the wyl and power of man, then can it be ſhonned and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyded, that is to ſay, a man maye chuſe, whether he will ſin or not. Where vpon I may conclude that eyther God is vnrighteous in pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing
<pb facs="tcp:1437:38"/> menne for the thynge, that they be dryuen vnto dy neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitye, or that we haue free wyll to do what we liſt. Which thynge ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to be moſte true, by the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, that God dothe ſpeake vnto Cain,<note place="margin">gene. iiii</note> ſaying: if thou doſt euyl, thy ſynne lyeth open in the doore. Let it be ſubdued vnto thee, and rule thou it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label> Thys obiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, were the Pelagians wont to make againſt Sainte Auguſtyne. Howe be it, I wyll not burden them wyth ſuch abhomynable he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſyes, til we haue fully diſcuſſed the hole matter.</p>
               <p>Fyrſte and foremoſt I ſaye, that ſynne oughte neuertheleſſe to bee imputed, thoughe it be of neceſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye. For, if anye manne woulde dyſpute wyth GOD, or woulde vnder thys pretence eſcape hys iudgement, becauſe that he coulde do none otherwyſe, he hathe thys anſwer ready.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1437:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Thy deſtruction commeth of thee, O Iſraell,<note place="margin">Oſee. iii.</note> but in me onlye is thy healpe. For, whence commeth this vnableneſſe or neceſſitye, that manne goeth about to excuſe hym ſelfe by, but of the corruption of hys nature? And whence commeth thys corruptyon, but that manne dyd rebell againſte God hys crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour? If all men be giltye of thys diſobedience and rebellyon, lette them not thyncke, that they ſhalbe excuſed by neceſſity, wherein they haue a moſt euident cauſe of theyr damnation.</p>
               <p>Saint Auguſtine doth expounde it none otherwyſe than I do,<note place="margin">Contra fortunat diſpu. xi.</note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaythe: I do boldlye affyrme, that free wyl was in that manne, that was created fyrſt, for he was ſo made, that nothing could wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand his wil, if he wold haue kept the commaundements. But after that he hath ſynned throughe hys fre wyll, he dyd caſt vs all that be come of hys ſtocke into neceſſitye.
<pb facs="tcp:1437:39" rendition="simple:additions"/> This neceſſity then, that we be in, commeth of the diſobedience and rebellion of our fyrſt pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Adam. Therfore no vnrighteouſneſſe can be imputed vnto God, thoughe he puniſheth vs for thoſe ſynnes that we be dryuen vnto by the ſame ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſitye, that we haue of the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall corruption of oure owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Secondlye where they ſaye, that if ſinne lieth in the wyll of man, it may be ſhonned and auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,<note place="margin">Man is not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of his</note> that is to ſaye. We may chuſe whether we ſin or not, that ſame were moſte true, if man were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of hys own wyl. But we haue alreadye proued, that the wyll of man, afore he be renued in Chriſt, and reſtored againe by his holye ſpirit, ſs in the thraldome and bon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dage of ſinne, and can in no wyſe be deliuered from it, till the ſonne of God hath made it fre by his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſpirite. In the meane ſeaſon, I meane,<note place="margin">Iohn. viii</note> while it is free from righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and ſeruaunt vnto ſyn,
<pb facs="tcp:1437:39" rendition="simple:additions"/> it can do no more but ſinne ſtil, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordinge to his corrupted nature. Yea, we do learne by the woordes of Paule,<note place="margin">Rom. vii</note> whiche were rehearſed euen now, what ſtrife and battail there is in the wyll of manne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing already renewed in Chriſt, ſo that many times he cannot do the good thing that he would, and the euel that he woulde not, the ſame is he fayne to do, ſo violente is the remnaunte of ſinne, that contynu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in manne alwayes vnto hys lyues end.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DYDIMVS.</speaker>
               <p>But what ſay ye to the place, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiectiō </seg>
                  </label> which was aledged oute of Geneſis, where the Lord ſaithe theſe wordes vnto Caine: if thou doſte euill,<note place="margin">gene. iiii.</note> thy ſinne lieth open in the dore. Lette it be ſubdued vnto thee, and rule thou it? do not theſe wordes declare plainly that ſinne lieth in the power of manne, and that he maye rule it, as it pleaſeth hym?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHI.</speaker>
               <p>Ye ſhall vnderſtande that <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1437:40" rendition="simple:additions"/> this place hath bene euyll tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of the Hebrewe.<note place="margin">The place of geneſis being ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected by the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies hath ben per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted.</note> For, wher they ſhould haue ſayed interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely, and in the maſculine gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: Shall he then be ſubdued vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, and wilt thou rule him? They did put awaye the interro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue poynt, &amp; did ſetfourth the ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tharticle of neuter ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der as though it ought to be referred vnto ſynne whereof he ſpake be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DIDyMVS.</speaker>
               <p>I would fayne heare what ye can make of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>It is not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen vnto you,<note place="margin">How the place of geneſis ought to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtanded.</note> that both Abell and Cain had offred ſacrifices vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the LORDE, Cain of the fruyte of the earthe, and Abell of the fyrſtlynges of hys ſhepe and of the fatte of them, and that the Lord had a reſpect vnto Abell &amp; his offring, but not vnto Cain nor yet to his ſacryfice. Wherfore he was exceadinge wrothe, ſo that his countenance chaunged.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1437:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Nowe we muſt conſyder the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,<note place="margin">Why A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice was accepted before god, and Cains ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crifice re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected. Heb. xi. Ro xiiii.</note> why Abell and his offring did pleaſe God, and why againe God had no pleaſure in Cain nor yet in his offringe. Forſoth becauſe that Abell did offer wyth faythe, and the other wythoute faythe. What ſoeuer then Cain did, was ſynne. For, wythoute faythe it is vnpoſſyble to pleaſe God? &amp; what ſoeuer is not of faythe, is ſynne. Therefore, Caine had more iuſte occaſyon to be angrye wyth hym ſelfe, and wyth hys vnbelief, than wyth hys brother Abell, who was both innocent, and dyd walcke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightlye before God, doing al that he dyd wyth a ſynceare and pure fayth. That therfore Cain might the better perceyue hys own ſaut the LORDE doothe playnlye declare vnto hym, that all that he dyd, was ſynne. Elſſe if he had done well ſhoulde not he haue ben as well regarded, as hys brother Abell.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1437:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>But his vnfaithfulneſſe, that dyd lie in his hearte, did witneſſe that he did not walke vprightly before god. Which thing he vnderſtode, when he ſaide: if thou doſte euyll, doth not thy ſinne lie open in the dore? That is to ſaye: if thou doſte the thing that thou doſt vnfaithful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye, dothe not thy conſcience beare record of the ſame, and is alwaies readye to condempne thee? What cauſe haſte thou then to be angrye with thy brother,<note place="margin">In thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that pertain to the true worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinge of god we muſt be ſubiect vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to noman but vnto the word of god onely.</note> becauſe that he doth walke vprightly before me, and with a pure and ſincere faith: ſhal he be ſubiect vnto thee in ſuch thinges, or ſhall he be ruled by the in thinges that pertaine to the true worſhippynge of me?</p>
               <p>Some do reade it withoute an interrogatife poynt on this wiſe: he ſhall be ſubiecte vnto thee, and thou ſhalt rule him. Wherby they do vnderſtande, that when Caine did ſee that his brother Abell was
<pb facs="tcp:1437:41"/> in ſuch fauour with God, he was affrayed leaſt he ſhoulde loſe the righte of the firſt borne, and that Abell ſhould be his Lord and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. And for this cauſe he did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue a deadly hatred againſt him, ſeekinge all maner of meanes to rydde him oute of the waye. The Lord therfore, for to put him out of that foolyſhe feare, that he was in, did certifye him, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandinge the fauoure that he dyd beare vnto Abel, he ſhuld not loſe one iote of his dignity and honour but that Abell ſhoulde accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge to the ryght and order of his byrth be ſubiecte and obedient vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hym ſtyll.</p>
               <p>Thus doth Chriſoſtome expound thys place of Geneſis.<note place="margin">Chrſoſt. in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſim.</note> Whoſe words but for tediouſneſſe I wold haue here aleadged, as they doe lye in his expoſition vpon the firſt booke of Moſes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DIDY.</speaker>
               <p>If both vertu and vice do not come of the free election of <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiectiō </seg>
                  </label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1437:42" rendition="simple:additions"/> the minde: Whye ſhoulde man be puniſhed for vice, or rewarded for vertue?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>This argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente did the Pelagians vſe alſo, as Sainte Ierome dothe write re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hercinge their very wordes which are theſe:<note place="margin">Epiſto. ad cteſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phontem &amp; dialo. i.</note> 
                  <hi>Quod ſi gratia dei in nobis agit, illa ergo, non nos qui non laboramus coronabitur.</hi> That is to ſay: If the grace of God dothe worke in vs, therefore it ſhall be crowned, and not we that laboure not. As tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinge puniſhementes, I ſaye, that we do deſeruingly ſuffer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">What we ought to iudge of the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment for ſynne</note> ſythe that ſynne cometh of oure ſelues. For, what dothe it ſkyll whether we ſynne throughe free wil or other wyſe, ſyth that of our owne nature we be ſynne altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yea and the bounde ſlaues of fynne? doth not Sainte Paul ſaye that of oure owne nature we are the chyldren of wrathe?<note place="margin">Ephe. ii.</note> If we be the children of wrathe, what are we elles but chyldren of damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb facs="tcp:1437:42"/> and fyre brondes of hell? And as touching the rewards of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, what abſurditye were it to ſaie that they come of the free mercye of God,<note place="margin">What we ought to iudge of the to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe. Rom. vi.</note> rather than of our owne merytes and deſeruinges? Doth not Saint Paule ſaye, that lyfe euerlaſtynge is the gyfte of God? How could lyfe euerlaſting, whyche is the moſt ſure rewarde of good woorkes, be the gyfte of God, excepte it were freelye geuen? But yf they woulde heare of what begynninge the holye A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtell dothe fetche the glorye of the Saints, they ſhoulde eaſely eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pye out their own errour: Whom (ſayeth he) he hathe choſen,<note place="margin">Ro. viii.</note> them did he call, whome he hath called, them did he iuſtifye, and whom he hathe iuſtifyed them dyd hee gloryfye.</p>
               <p>Wherefore then, by the ſayinge of the Apoſtell are the faythfull crowned wyth eternall and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtynge glorye?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1437:43"/>
               <p>becauſe forſouth that by the free mercye of God, and not by their owne induſtrye, they be both cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, called and iuſtifyed. Whye ſhould any man fear then, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ther ſhoulde be no more merites if free wyll were ouerthrowen? Or why ſhoulde any manne flye from that thinge, that the ſrcipture doth call vs to? What haſte thou (ſayeth ſaint Paule) that thou haſt not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued?<note place="margin">i. Cor. iiii</note> And if thou haſt receaued, why doſt thou boaſt, as thoughe thou haddeſt not receiued? Ye ſee that he dothe therfore take awaye all thynges from free wyll, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that he wold leaue no place vnto merites. But God as he is rych in doyng good vnto all men, ſo the gyftes that he geueth vnto vs, l e maketh them oure owne, and ſo rewardeth them as oure owne.</p>
               <p>And therefore Sainte Auguſtine ſayeth:<note place="margin">Epiſt. lii</note> 
                  <hi>Nihil es per te. Peccata tua ſunt, merita autem dei.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1437:43"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Supplicium tibi debetur: et cum premium venerit, ſua d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>na coronabit non meritae tua:</hi> that is to ſaye: Thou arte no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by thy ſelfe. The ſinnes are thyne owne, but the merites are of God. Puniſhment is due vnto the and when the reward dothe come, he ſhall crowne his giftes,<note place="margin">In Pſal. lxx.</note> and not thy merits. And in an other place theſe be alſo his woordes: <hi>Si redde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur tibi quod debetur puniendus es. Quid ergo fit? Non tibi reddit deus deb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tam penam, ſed donat indeb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tam grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am. Si vis eſſe alienus a gratia <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>acta me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rita tua.</hi> Whiche we maye Engliſh after this manner: if that be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred or payed vnto thee, that is due, thou muſte bee punyſhed. What is done then? God dothe not render or paye vnto thee the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment that is due or deſerued: but he geueth vnto thee, the grace that is neyther due nor deſerued. If thou wylte be putte from the grace, boſte forthe thyne own me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites.
<pb facs="tcp:1437:44"/> But what nede I: to aledge any more ſayings of his, ſyth that all his workes, be full of ſuche ſentences? Whereby it dothe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, that he dothe adſcribe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge at all vnto the merites of men, but all together vnto the free mercy and goodneſſe of God. And therfore the argument that ye did brynge, maye rather be called the argumente of an heatheniſh philoſopher, than the argument of a Chriſtian doctoure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiectiō </seg>
                  </label> Thys was alſo one of theyr arguments, wherby they went about to proue that we haue free wyll.</p>
               <p>Wherfore, ſay they, ſhoulde any exhortations be made vnto the people, or wherfore ſhoulde they be rebuked for their ſinnes, if it lieth not in them to obey, or if it lyeth not in theyr power to ſhon vice and to embrace vertue?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>Suche ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iections
<pb facs="tcp:1437:44"/> were made vnto S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine,<note place="margin">Aunſwer made out of ſainte Auguſt.</note> wherfore he was compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to make a boke <hi>de correptione et gratia,</hi> that is to ſay: of rebukynge and of grace. Wher he doth ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confute all the obiections and argumentes that the aduerſaryes can make,<note place="margin">In his de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>correptio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne &amp; gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia.</note> which maye be reduced and brought to this ſhort and com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pendious ſumme: O man, knowe in the commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, what thou art bound to do. In the rebuking, learne that throughe thyne owne faut thou haſt it not, and in praier learn whence thou muſt receiue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou wilt haue. Firſt, we are not alone in this cauſe, but Chriſt &amp; al his apoſtles. Let them ſe how they can ſhift, hauing to do with ſuch aduerſaries. Becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſt ſaith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we can do nothinge without him,<note place="margin">Iohn. xv.</note> dothe he leſſe rebuke them therefore that withoute him did euil? or dyd he leſſe exhorte all men to geue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues vnto good woorkes? Howe ſharpelye dothe
<pb facs="tcp:1437:45"/> Saint Paule inueighe againſt the Corinthians for the neglecting of chriſtian loue and charity? and yet at lengthe he deſireth of God, that he vouchſafe to geue them chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an loue and charity.<note place="margin">i. Cor. xvi</note> Wrytinge to the Romaines, he doth teſtify that it lieth not in the wyl and renning of man, but in the mercye of God: yet afterwardes he dothe not ceaſe to admoniſhe,<note place="margin">Rom. ix.</note> to exhorte and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke. Why doe they not therefore warne the Lord, or geue him coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſel, that he do not loſe his labour, requiring thoſe thinges of menne which he alone is able to geue? Or rebuking them for thoſe thinges, which only throughe the lacke of hys grace are committed? Why do they not warn Paul to ſpare them in whoſe power it lieth not to wil nor to renne, without the mercye of God, wherof they be al together deſtituted? As thoughe the Lord is not able to ſhewe a ſufficient rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or cauſe of his doctrin, whiche
<pb facs="tcp:1437:45"/> in dede doth offer it ſelf vnto them that do godly and reuerently ſeke for it. Verely S. Paule dothe well declare and ſhew how much,<note place="margin">i. Cor. i.</note> both exhorting, and rebukinge are able by them ſelues to change the min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the hearers, when he wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, that neyther he that planteth is any thing, nor he that watreth, but that it is the Lord that geueth the encreaſe, which only worketh effectuouſly. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion </seg>
                  </label> Wherfore then do the exhortations ſerue? <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label> If they that be of an obſtinate hearte doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne and deſpiſe them, they ſhall be for a witneſſe vnto them, when they come before the iudgemente ſeat of Chriſte. Yea nowe at thys preſent, they do already beate and ſmite theyr conſciences: For, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they laugh them to ſcorn, yet they be not able to dyſalowe them. But what ſhoulde they doe? Sith that the ſoftneſſe of the hart, which is neceſſary vnto obedience is denied vnto theym? yea rather
<pb facs="tcp:1437:46" rendition="simple:additions"/> what are they able to ſay, ſith that they can impute the ſame hardnes of their own harts, but only to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues? but the chief vtility is to be conſidered in the faithfull: For, as the Lord doth woorke in them, all thinges by his holy ſpirit, ſo dothe he not neglect y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inſtrument of his word, nor yet occupy it, wythoute efficacy or effect. Let therefore the truth ſtand, that is to ſaye, let all menne be ſure of this, that all the hole ſtrengthe and vertue of the godlye dothe lye only in the grace of God.<note place="margin">An other queſtion.</note> Whye be they warned of theyr duetye, and not rather per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted all together vnto the guy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or gouernment of the ſpirit? Why are they ſtirred and moued with exhortations, ſythe that they can make no more haſte, than the ſpirite dothe pricke them forwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des: whye are they rebuked, if they go at any time out of the way: ſith that they fall through the weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of theyr fleſhe? O man what
<pb facs="tcp:1437:46" rendition="simple:additions"/> arte thou, that dareſt preſcrybe a law vnto God?<note place="margin">Aunſwer</note> If by exhortatyon he wyll haue vs to be prepared to receiue the ſame ſelf grace, where by we are made obedient vnto his word: is there any thing that thou canſt iuſtly reproue in this deuine policye of his? If exhortations and rebukings ſhuld ſerue for nothing els amonge the godlye, but for to rebuke ſynne, they oughte not to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted vnprofitable. But now,<note place="margin">The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fytte of ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vnto the godlye.</note> ſith that the ſpirite workynge in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardlye, they doe profyte muche for to kyndle in menne a deſyre of goodneſſe, to ſhake of ſlouggiſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe, to take awaye the pleaſure of wyckedneſſe, and the poyſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſweeteneſſe of it: and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarywiſe for to engender in them a hatred and tediouſneſſe of vyce, and of this wicked and ſynnefull world, who dareth ſaye that they be ſuperflue or vnprofitable?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1437:47"/>
               <speaker>EVTRAPELVS</speaker>
               <p>Here in deede S. Auguſtin doth anſwer through<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly the vain obiections of the Pela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gians, ſo that any reaſonable man oughte to contente him ſelfe wyth his anſwer. How be it, me thinke that they were ſufficiently anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red already in our firſte communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, that we haue had this mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyng of the deuine predeſtinatyon of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>Thys haue I gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out of the wordes of S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin:<note place="margin">What maye be gathered of Saint Auguſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes.</note> that God doth two manner of waies worke in hys elect and cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen: Inwardly wyth his holye ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and outwardly with his word with his ſpirite he maketh theym new creatures, lightenynge theyr mindes, and kindeling theyr har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes with the loue of righteouſnes. With his woorde, he dothe moue and ſtyrre them to deſire the ſame renewing, to ſeke for it, and to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace it. And to both of them doth he retch forth his hand effectuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb facs="tcp:1437:47" rendition="simple:additions"/> according as he hathe appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ordained.<note place="margin">Why god doth ſend his word vnto the reprate.</note> And when he doth ſend his word vnto the repro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bate, thoughe it be not for theyr a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment, yet it is to thys ende, that they may in this preſet world be confounded with the teſtimony and witneſſe of theyr owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ence, and alſo be made vnexcuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble agaynſt the day of iudgement. But what can ye ſay to theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the ſcripture, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiectiō </seg>
                  </label> that they did a leadge vnto me: I wyl willinglye offer ſacrifice vnto thee. Agayne: I wyll of my free wyll praiſe and laude thee. Item: Let thyne hande be readye to ſaue me: For, I haue choſen thy commaundements? Do not theſe wordes of the prophette Dauid declare plainlye, that the thing, that he did, he did it willing<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, frely and frankly?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILA.</speaker>
               <p>I ſaye, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label> that they make or put no difference betwyxte the man that is alreadye renewed by the ſpirite of God, and the manne
<pb facs="tcp:1437:48"/> that is altogether carnal and fleſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly. For, the man that is not rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated or borne of newe, wyll ſpeake no ſuch woordes as Dauid dyd. For, they are the wordes of a manne, that is alreadye made a newe creature by the Spirite of God. This will then that was in Dauid did not come of hys owne ſelf nor of his fre will that he had of his owne nature: but it did com of the ſpirit of God, who dyd geue this will vnto Dauid. For, Ieſus Chriſt him ſelfe doth ſay: Verely, verelye I ſaye vnto you:<note place="margin">Iohn. iii</note> excepte a manne be borne from aboue, he can not ſee the kingdome of God. Where by he dothe meane, that manne is able to doe nothynge that is pleaſaunte or acceptable vnto GOD. Nor yet taſte the ſweteneſſe of the heauenly king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, excepte it be geuen vnto him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>If (ſaid thei vnto me) we haue no free wil, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiectiō </seg>
                  </label> why ſhoulde
<pb facs="tcp:1437:48"/> God ſo manye times call ſynners vnto repentaunce? were it not la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour loſt ſo to do? How manye ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes doth he by his Prophets crye out and ſay: Turne ye vnto me, al ye endes of the earthe,<note place="margin">Eſay. xlv</note> and ſo ſhall ye be ſaued? Againe: Tourne vnto me and repent.<note place="margin">Eze. xviii</note> If menne haue not fre wil to do theſe thinges the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phets do labor in vaine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>If ye marke wel the talke and communication of youre faithfull guides, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">aunſwer </seg>
                  </label> ye ſhall eaſelye perceiue, that they be not throughlye exerciſed in the ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. For, God doth not ſo ſpeake vnto menne by hys Prophettes, becauſe that ſynners are able of theyr own ſelues to turn vnto hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DIDyMVS.</speaker>
               <p>Howe be ye able to proue that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES..</speaker>
               <p>Firſt, wher Eſay ſaithe:<note place="margin">Eſay. xlv</note> in the perſons of the Lorde: Tourne ye vnto me, and ye ſhall be healed: by and by Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye dothe crye oute and ſaye: O
<pb facs="tcp:1437:49"/> Lord, turne me, and I ſhalbe tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. For, thou arte the Lorde my God. Yea, aſſone, as thou turneſt me, I ſhal reforme my ſelf. Again: the Lorde dothe commaunde, that we ſhoulde circumciſe oure owne heartes:<note place="margin">Iere. iiii.</note> yet by Moſes he dothe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that the ſame circumciſion is made with his owne hande.<note place="margin">Deut. xxx</note> He doth alſo require the renewing of our heartes: but in an other place, he doth plainly teſtify, that it is he him ſelf that geueth it. Loke ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, what God doth promiſe, that do we not by oure free will or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (as S. Auguſtine ſaithe) but GOD dothe it, by his grace. And this is the fift thing,<note place="margin">The rule of Tiro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius.</note> that he dothe bid vs to marke amonge the rules of Tironius, that is to ſay, that we ſhoulde note diligentlye the dyffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence that is betwixt the law and the promiſes or betwixte the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes and the grace. I maye here bringe in, manye other lyke places:<note place="margin">Act. xv.</note> Paule and Barnabas
<pb facs="tcp:1437:49"/> do exhorte the faythfull to abyde and perſeuer in the grace of God. But Paule in an other place doth ſhewe, whence, that vertue of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancye and perſeueraunce dothe come:<note place="margin">Ephe. vi.</note> fynally my bretherne (ſaith he) be ſtrong in the Lorde. Again: for this cauſe do I bowe my knees vnto the father of oure Lord Ieſu Chriſte, that he woulde graunte you accordinge to the rycheſſe of his glory, that ye maye be ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed wyth might, by the ſpirit of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inner man, that Chriſt may dwell in your hartes by faith.</p>
               <p>Moreouer he ſayeth: Greue not the holye ſpyrit of God,<note place="margin">Ephe. iiii</note> by whom ye are ſealed vnto redemption.</p>
               <p>But the thynge that he doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyre there, becauſe that it canne not be perfourmed by menne, he doth deſyre God to graunte it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Theſſalonians, ſayinge:<note place="margin">i. Theſ. i.</note> wherfore, we pray alwayes for you, that your god make you wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of your callinge, and fulfyll al
<pb facs="tcp:1437:50"/> good purpoſe of his goodneſſe and the worke of fayth wyth power, that the name of oure Lorde Ieſu Chriſt, maye be glorifyed in you, and ye in hym throughe the grace of our God, and of the Lord Ieſu Chriſt. Theſe places do ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declare, that what ſo euer God dothe requyre of vs, the ſame he muſt worke in vs by his holye ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite. For, of our ſelues we are able to do no maner of thing, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good is?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DIDY.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion </seg>
                  </label> Why doth God the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpeake after this maner vnto men?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHI.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label> God cauſeth men to be thus admoniſhed and warned, becauſe that it is a meane, that he hathe appoynted and ordayned. And whiche he dothe vſe, for to illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and lighten thoſe that be elec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted and choſe vnto life euerlaſting and for to make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to know their ſinnes. For, god by the preaching of his worde, &amp; by the vertue of his holy ſpirite, doth geue vnto them that be choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto lyfe euerlaſting
<pb facs="tcp:1437:50" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſtrength to turn vnto him. And al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>though this doctrin of conuerſyon or turning is directed vnto all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> generally, yet doth it moſt chieflye pertain vnto the elect and choſen, vnto whom by this meane, God il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminating them, doth geue pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and ſtrength to conuert or turn. Againe:<note place="margin">Why God cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth obſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nate ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to be warned.</note> God cauſeth obſtynate ſynners to be thus warned by his Prophets, becauſe that they ſhuld not pretend ignorance, nor excuſe them ſelues by it in the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God. And alſo for to ſhewe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he loueth vertue, &amp; rightouſneſſe, and that he is not author of euil. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God did ſend Moſes vnto Pharao,<note place="margin">Exo. vii.</note> God knew right wel that Pharao wold not turne. Yet we muſt not ſay that God did ſend him in vain.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBI.</speaker>
               <p>Thus they ſaid vnto me: <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiectiō </seg>
                  </label> wherfore do theſe promiſes ſerue: ſeke after the thing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is good, and not euill, ſo ſhall ye liue:<note place="margin">Amos. v</note> yea the lord god of hoſtes ſhalbe with you accordinge to your owne deſires.
<pb facs="tcp:1437:51"/> Againe: If ye be louinge and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, ye ſhal enioye the beſt thing that groweth in the lande: but if ye be obſtinate and rebellious, ye ſhal be deuoured with the ſwerde. For the mouthe of the Lord hathe ſpoken it.<note place="margin">Iere. iiii.</note> Item: if thou wylt put away thy abhominations oute of my ſight thou ſhalt not be dryuen oute. If thou ſhalt harken vnto the voyce of the Lorde thy God, to obſerue and do all his commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements,<note place="margin">Deut. xxv Le. xxviii</note> which I commaund the this daye, then ſhall the Lord thy God ſet the aboue all nations vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth. And ſuch other lyke: ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte we haue free wyll, or except it lyeth in oure power to fulfyll and perfourme the condytions, that are annexed vnto them? we maye ſaye in deede that they be goodlye promyſes, if the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that be annexed vnto them, canne not be perfourmed by oure owne ſtrengthe and power: and that God dothe playe mocke holy
<pb facs="tcp:1437:51"/> daye wyth vs, if he promyſethe thynges, that it lyeth not in vs to obtayne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALE.</speaker>
               <p>And I ſaye that it is a playne blaſphemye, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label> to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrme that God doth playe mocke holy daye wyth vs, when he doth prouoke vs to deſerue his benefits although he knoweth vs to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to do it. For, when the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are offered vnto the faythfull &amp; vngodly in lyke,<note place="margin">The ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte of Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſes both in the godly and in the vngodly.</note> they haue their effect and working in them bothe. For, as God dothe by his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes pricke the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of the vngodly, leſt putting away altogether the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce of his iudgementes, they ſhoulde haue to much pleaſure in ſynne: ſo by his promiſes he doth teſtify and declare vnto them, how vnworthy they are of his liberality, &amp; good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. For, who woulde ſaye that it is not mete and conueniente,<note place="margin">Marke this dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentely.</note> that the Lorde ſhoulde do good vnto them, that do worſhip him?
<pb facs="tcp:1437:52"/> And that againe, he ſhoulde accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge to his ſeueritye and iuſtyce, take vengaunce of theym that are deſpiſers of his maieſty? Therfore it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be ſaid, but that God doth iuſtlye, when in his promiſes, he dothe preſcribe and geue ſuche a law and condition vnto the vngod<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye, whiche be wrapped in ſinne, that they ſhall receiue and enioye hys benefites, if they doe forſake their wickedneſſe, althoughe hee ſhoulde do it onlye for thys cauſe, that they maye vnderſtande that they are iuſtlye and deſeruinglye put from thoſe thinges, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are due vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true worſhippers of God. Again: ſith that God, dothe by all meanes prouoke the faithful to cal for his grace, why ſhuld not he as wel attempte the ſame by his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes, as by his law and ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dements? being taught the wyl of God by his commaundements, we are warned of our owne miſerye, becauſe that of oure own nature,
<pb facs="tcp:1437:52"/> we do all together diſſent and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agre from it: and alſo we are mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to cal vppon the ſpirit of god, for to bring vs into the right way. But becauſe that oure ſluggyſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is ſuch,<note place="margin">Why pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſes are made vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs.</note> that it can not be put awaye nor ſhaken of, by the lawe and commaundements of god: pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſſes are added, that ſo by ſome ſweteneſſe we might be prouoked and allured to the loue of heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things. Now, the more deſirous that we are of the true ryghteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, the more feruent are we to cal for the grace of God. Theſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges beynge well conſidered, who would ſay, that ſuche promiſes be vnprofitable, though we be not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to fulfil the conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, that are annered vnto them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRAPELVS.</speaker>
               <p>No manne, I trowe,<note place="margin">What the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate do learne by the promi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes of god</note> that hathe anye cromme of godlye vnderſtandinge in hys bellye. For, by them the reprobate &amp; vngodlye do learne how vnwor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thy they are of the bounteous libe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rality
<pb facs="tcp:1437:53"/> and goodneſſe of almighty God: &amp; the godlye,<note place="margin">What the godly do learne by the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dition an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nexed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myſes.</note> when they ſee in the conditions, that be annexed vnto them, their owne miſery, weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, infirmitye and vnableneſſe, are ſtirred and moued by the ſame to cal more earneſtly, for the grace of God, and for the aſſiſtaunce and help of his holy ſpirit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiectiō </seg>
                  </label> The Lord doth laye to the Iſraelites charge, that it was only longe of them, that they did not receiue all kinde of libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and goodneſſe at hys hande. As when the Prophet ſayth: Ama<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leck and the Cananites are before you,<note place="margin">numbers xiiii. Iere. vii.</note> with whoſe ſwordes ye ſhall be deſtroyed, becauſe ye wolde not obey the Lord. Becauſe I haue cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led you, and ye haue not aunſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red nor obeyed: therfore, will I do vnto this houſe, as I haue don vn to Silo. Again: This people hath not harkened vnto the voyce of the Lord theyr God, nor receaued hys doctrine: Therfore, the Lord hath
<pb facs="tcp:1437:53"/> caſte them of. Item. Becauſe that ye haue hardened your heartes,<note place="margin">Ier. xxxii</note> &amp; woulde not be obedient vnto the Lorde: All theſe plages haue hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened vnto you. Howe coulde the Iſraelites be caſt in the tethe with ſuch thinges, except it had lyen in them to ſhonne and auoyde thoſe thinges, that be there laied to their charge? For they might haue aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered by and by: We had a mind to proſperity,<note place="margin">How the vngodlye do al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies go aboute to excuſe them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues.</note> and did fear trouble and aduerſity: but that we did not obey the Lorde, nor harcken vnto his voyce, that we might obtayne the one, and eſchue the other, it was becauſe that we are vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bondage of ſynne, and can not doe frely the thinges, that we would. Thoſe thinges then are not iuſtly laid to oure charge whiche it ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not in our power for to ſhonne or auoid.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>As for the pretence of neceſſity, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label> wherby ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners go about to excuſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues,
<pb facs="tcp:1437:54" rendition="simple:additions"/> it hath ben al ready declared, what pore healpe can be had in it, ſythe that the cauſe Originall, and of ſpring of it, is in our owne ſelues, by oure naturall corruption, that we haue of our firſt parent Adam. Therfore, I do aſke whether they can proue them ſelues to be wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out faut or not? For, if there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny faut in them: it is not wythout a cauſe, that God did caſte them in the teethe, that it was throughe their owne wickedneſſe, that they did not feele the frute of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and mercy. Can they ſay nay but that theyr wicked and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted will is the cauſe of their rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyous contumacye and ſtubburne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? If they fynde that the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne and well ſprynge of theyr owne euyl and miſerye is wythin them ſelues: what do they trauail to finde out outwarde cauſes, and all becauſe that they wil not ſeme to be the authoures of theyr owne deſtruction? If it be true then, that
<pb facs="tcp:1437:54"/> ſynners throughe theyr own faut are both depriued of the benefites of God, and alſo puniſhed and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged: there is a good cauſe, whye they ſhoulde heare ſuche vpbray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynges and reproches at the mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the of the Lorde. That if they doe obſtinately perſeuer and continue in ſynne, they may learne in theyr miſeries and calamities, to accuſe and deteſt theyr owne wickednes, rather than to lay any vniuſte and cruell ſeueritye vnto God: or if they be not vtterlye geuen ouer, they may, beinge wearye of theyr ſynnes, wherefore they ſee theym ſelues thus extreamelye plaged, come into the way again, acknow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledginge the ſame wyth earneſt confeſſion, that the Lord doth laye to their charge.<note place="margin">Note this</note> This effecte haue the chidinges and rebukinges of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophets amonge the godly: as it doth appere by the ſolemne prayer of Daniell,<note place="margin">Dani. vi.</note> which is wrytten in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ninthe chapiter of hys prophecye.
<pb facs="tcp:1437:55" rendition="simple:additions"/> But how ſuch ſharpe rebukinges of the prophets of God, take place amonge the obſtinate ſinners, we haue an example of it in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes, vnto whome Ieremye was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to ſhew the cauſe of their miſeries and calamities,<note place="margin">Iere. vii.</note> although it ſhoulde be none otherwyſe than God had appoynted, &amp; told before. Thou ſhalt, ſaith the Lord, ſpeke vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al theſe wordes, and they ſhal not hear, thou ſhalt cal them, and they ſhal not anſwer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DYDIMVS.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiectiō </seg>
                  </label> For what purpoſe, were thoſe thynges ſpoken vnto them, that would not hear?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label> That, wold they, nild they, they ſhould be fain to vnderſtande, that the ſame was true, that was told vnto them, and that it was a plain ſacriledge and robbing of the glory of God, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe vnto him the cauſe of theyr calamities and miſeries, whyche was in them ſelues. With theeſe few ſolutions &amp; anſwers, any man
<pb facs="tcp:1437:55" rendition="simple:additions"/> may eaſely rid him ſelfe from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye authorities, whiche the enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes of the grace of God, are wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to heape together for to erect, and ſette vppe the Idoll of theyr free wyll.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>This is moſte ſure, that the Lorde dothe ſpeake theſe woordes by his prophet Oſeas: <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiectiō </seg>
                  </label> I wyll go, and retourn to my place,<note place="margin">Oſee. v.</note> tyll they waxe faint, and ſeke me. It were a foliſh thing (ſaid my gen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tle men vnto me) if the LORD ſhould tary til Iſrael ſhuld tourne and ſeeke hym, except it dyd lie in theyr power to tourn which waye they liſted.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILA.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <note place="margin">The ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies can wynne nothinge vpon vs by the threate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of god.</note>As thoughe the Lorde doth not commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly in the prophets make as though he ſhould forſake and caſte of, hys people, tyll they amend and tourne vnto hym: but what are oure ennemyes able to gather of ſuche threatnynges? If they go about to gather by them, that men beinge forſaken of God,
<pb facs="tcp:1437:56"/> are of their owne ſelues able to turne againe, then haue they all the ſcriptures againſt them: If they ſaye that they haue neede of the garce of God, that they maye turne again: what neede they to contende or ſtriue with vs?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DIDYMVS.</speaker>
               <p>They do not denye but that the grace of God is nece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſarye: if ye wyll graunte that there is alſo in manne a certayne ſtrength.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>Howe ſhall they be able to prone that. Truely they can not proue it by this place nor by ſuche like. For, it is an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thynge to go away from man and to looke, what beyng permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and lefte vnto hym ſelfe he is able to do, and an other thynge to healpe hys ſmall ſtrength, as hys imbecilitye and weakeneſſe dothe requyre.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DYDIMVS.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion </seg>
                  </label> What doth the lord meane then by ſuche manner of ſpeakyng.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1437:56"/>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>It is euen as if he ſhoulde ſay: <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label> Syth that this rebellious people wyll take no heede to my warnings and exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, nor yet to my ſharpe rebukinges, I wyll for a tyme wythdrawe my ſelf from him, and ſuffer him to be afflycted, and troubled. I wyll ſee whether this ſtyfnecked people, wyll at length after theyr greate calamityes, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, and troubles, remember me and ſeke my face. Nowe,<note place="margin">What it is meant when the ſcripture ſayeth that God doth with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>drawe him ſelfe from this people.</note> when the ſcripture ſayeth, that God dothe wythdraw hym ſelf, the meaning of it is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God doth take away hys prophecye and worde, wher in he declareth a certain preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of hys. And to looke what men wyll do, it ſignifyeth that God wyll holde him ſelfe ſtyll, and as he were a ſleape, ſuffer them to be manye and ſondrye wayes plaged.</p>
               <p>And bothe theſe thynges, is he wont to doo, for to make vs to humble oure ſelues.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1437:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>For we ſhould rather by aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye be dryuen vnto deſperatyon, than vnto anye amendemente of lyfe, except he ſhould by his ſpirite make vs meete to receiue hys cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſement. Wherfore, to go about by ſuche places, for to proue that there is anye ſuch ſtrengthe in vs, or that we haue free wyll to doe what we liſt, it is a plain madnes. For, ſuch thinges be ſpoken in the ſcriptures for none other purpoſe, but for to make vs to know oure own infirmity and weakeneſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>I dyd aſke them, whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther they could bryng anye autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities of the ſcripture,<note place="margin">The ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection of the papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes.</note> whereby they myght proue expreſlye that a man hath ſuche free wyll, as they went about to maintaine and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold. They dyd then aunſwer me that Moſes was ſo ſure of it, that he did not doubt to ſay theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des vnto the children of Iſraell.<note place="margin">Deut. xxx</note> I take heauen and earth this day to record ouer you, that I haue layde
<pb facs="tcp:1437:57"/> before you, life and deathe, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and curſing. Chuſe life there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that thou mayeſt lyue thou and thy feede, and that ye maye loue the Lorde your God, and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vnto his voyce, and cleaue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him.<note place="margin">Ioſu. xxiiii.</note> Ioſua alſo did ſaye vnto the people: Chuſe ye this daye, whome ye wyll ſerue: The God whome youre fathers ſerued be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yonde the water, or the Goddes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Amorites in whoſe lande ye dwell. Thinke ye that theſe true ſeruaunts of God Moſes and Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſua, would haue ſpoken thus vnto the people, except it had lyen in their power to chuſe which they would? It is playne then that they had free wyll? elles ſuche things, hadde bene ſpoken vnto them in vaine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Aunſwer</note>Suche ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences and autoryties of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, do not proue that man hath free wyl to do what he lyſt, or that he can at his owne pleaſure chuſe
<pb facs="tcp:1437:58" rendition="simple:additions"/> both good and euil. For, although Moſes doth ſaye vnto the people: I do laye before you both life and death: yet it foloweth not, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were able of theyr owne ſelues to chuſe lyfe, without the ſpirit and grace of God.<note place="margin">Deu. xxix</note> Whiche thinge he doth ſufficientely declare in an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place when he ſayeth: Thyne eies haue ſene theſe greate tokens and wonders. Yet the Lorde hath not geuen. thee a harte to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande, nor eares to heare, nor eies to ſee. As then it did profytte the people nothinge to haue ſeene the greate tokens and wonders, that the Lord did worke in Egipt euen in theyr owne ſight, excepte he did geue them a harte to vnderſtande, eares to heare and eies to ſee, that is to ſaye, except the Lorde did by his holy ſpirit lyghten their harts vnſtop their eares, and cleare the eyes of theyr myndes: euen ſo, althoughe Moſes, Ioſua, and all the prophetes of God doe ſaye a
<pb facs="tcp:1437:58" rendition="simple:additions"/> thouſande time: Behold, we laye before you lyfe and death, chuſe whiche ye wyll: yet all this, wyll profytte vs nothinge, except God dothe worke inwardely wyth his holy ſpirit. Whiche thinge Saint Paule dothe neyther dyſſemble nor hydde, when he wryteth on thys manner.<note place="margin">i. Cor. i.</note> I haue planted and Apollo hathe watred, But it is the Lord that geueth the encreace. But that ye maye the better per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue the whole matter, ye ſhall vnderſtande that God doth by the preachinge of his prophetes and Apoſtles:<note place="margin">Mat. ix.</note> as when oure ſauioure Ieſu Chriſte dyd ſaye vnto the manne that was ſycke of the pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſye: aryſe, take vp thy bedde, and go home.</p>
               <p>It dyd not folowe, that he hadde ſtrengthe to aryſe, excepte oure ſauyoure Ieſus Chriſte hadde ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen it hym.</p>
               <p>But when Chryſte dyd ſaye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hym, aryſe:
<pb facs="tcp:1437:59"/> He did ſtreyght wyth it, geue him ſtrength to aryſe. Euen ſo, when God doth by his preachers ſpeake vnto them, whom he hath choſen already; and doth commaund them to aryſe oute of the bdde of ſynne, ſtreyght wyth, hee geueth them ſtrength to do it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DIDYMVS.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiectiō </seg>
                  </label> I maruayle that ye wyll haue no manner of ſtrength to bee lefte vnto vs, in thinges that perteyne to our ſaluation and lyfe euerlaſtinge ſyth that oure ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uioure Ieſus Crhiſt him ſelf doth teſtifye that the manne that went from Ieruſalem to Iericho,<note place="margin">luc. x.</note> by whom he vnderſtode al mankinde, was by the theues left halfe deade, and not dead altogether. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by anye man woulde iudge, that there is yet ſome parcell of lyfe in man, and that he hathe yet ſome ſparkles of righte vnderſtandinge and Godlye wyll remayninge in him. For, wherin els ſhoulde con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt that halfe of his lyfe, that was
<pb facs="tcp:1437:59" rendition="simple:additions"/> lefte vnto him by the theues, that had ſo ſore wounded him?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label> What if I woulde not geue place vnto theyr allegory, what could they ſay vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me? Could they lay any hereſye vnto me for it? For, it is wythout all doubt, that the fathers haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented the ſame allegory, beſydes the right meaning of our ſauioure Ieſu Chriſt. For, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcope or marke that our ſauior Ieſus Chriſt dothe ſhute at there, is to teache,<note place="margin">What marke that oure ſauioure Ieſus Chriſt doth ſhute at in the parable of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maritane How far parables ought to take place.</note> who is oure neighboure, and not to mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifye anye naturall ſtrengthe that was left in man. Let any manne, that wyll, reade the place, and he ſhall finde that it is ſo as I ſaye. Moreouer allegories ought to goe no farther, than they haue the rule of Gods word for their warrant: It is ſo farre of, that they ſhoulde ſuffiſe by them ſelues to grounde any doctrine. How be it let vs ſee what they ſhal gette by their alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory. We dyd all in oure firſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent
<pb facs="tcp:1437:60" rendition="simple:additions"/> Adam fall into the handes of the theues,<note place="margin">What ou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ght to be vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the allegorye of the wounded man.</note> I meane, of our enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye Sathan the deuil, by whome we wer ſtriped out of our clothes, wounded and left half dead. Firſt, we were ſtriped out of our clothes and lefte naked: what is mente by this, but that we were by our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my ſpoyled of oure naturall inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency and ryghteouſneſſe, yea and of all other heauenlye gyftes that we had receyued in our fyrſt crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion? And not onlye this, but alſo we were wounded and lefte halfe dead. That is to ſay: we were left a liue vnto oure ſelues, vnto the world, and vnto ſinne, but we wer lefte all together dead vnto God, and vnto heauenly thinges. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore,<note place="margin">Ephe. ii.</note> Saynt Paul ſpeakyng of our redemption, dothe not ſaye, that we were healed beyng half a lyue, but that when wee were deade throughe ſynne, God dyd quycken vs agayne wyth hys ſonne Ieſu Chriſt. And vnto thys, dothe oure
<pb facs="tcp:1437:60" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſauyoure hym ſelf agree,<note place="margin">Ioh. vi.</note> when he ſayeth: Verely, verely I ſaye vnto you: the houre will come, and is nowe already, that the deade ſhall heare the voyce of the Sonne of manne, and they that hear it ſhall lyue. Who durſte ſette an allego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye inuented by menne agaynſte ſo many playn textes of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>In deede when I doe conſider the circumſtaunces of the texte, I doe perceiue that their al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legory is farre from the meanyng of oure ſauioure Ieſus Chriſte. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: we doe plainelye learne by the authorityes that ye aledged e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen nowe, that we are all to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deade vnto GOD, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to heauenlye thynges, beynge ſpoyled of al thoſe excellent giftes that wee hadde receaued in oure fyrſte creatyon, as Dauyd dothe teſtifye ſayinge:<note place="margin">Pſal. xli.</note> Manne when he was in honoure, he dyd not vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb facs="tcp:1437:61"/> it, and therfore he was made like vnto brute beaſtes. How be it there be yet certain places behind, which by your patience, I intende now to bring fourth, that I maye be deliuered from all doubt.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Apo. iii. Obiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </note>The one is in the Reuelation of Ihon, where the Lord ſpeaketh on this manner: Behold, I ſtande at the dore and knocke. If anye man heare my voyce, and open the dore I wyll come in vnto him, and wyl ſuppe wyth him, and he with me. Thys place they haue alwayes in their mouthes, goinge aboute to proue thereby that we haue free wyll. Elſſe why ſhoulde the Lorde ſay that he ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth at the dore and knocke, and that if any man heare his voyce and open, he wyll come in vnto him? It were in vaine ſo to ſaye, excepte it did lie in man to heare the voyce of the Lord, and to open when ſo euer he doth knocke at the dore.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Aunſwer</note>Fyrſte and
<pb facs="tcp:1437:61" rendition="simple:additions"/> foremoſt: what do they vnderſtand by the doore, that the Lorde dothe knocke at?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>By the dore, they doe vnderſtand the harte of man.<note place="margin">What it is to be vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the dore that the lorde dothe knocke at</note> And they ſay that the lord doth knocke at our heartes by his word, when he doth by it cal vs vnto repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and amendement of life, and that we do ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto him, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we do re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiue his worde, and bryng forthe the frutes therof.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALE.</speaker>
               <p>When our ſauioure Ieſu Chriſte, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion </seg>
                  </label> did preache in hys owne perſone, and dyd knocke at mennes hartes by hys worde, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge them vnto repentaunce and amendement of life coulde any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> open vnto him, that is to ſay, to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiue his word, and bryng fourthe the frutes of it, excepte it were ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen hym.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>I thincke naye. For the truthe him ſelf ſaithe: <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label> No man can come vnto me except it be ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen him of my father. Againe in
<pb facs="tcp:1437:62" rendition="simple:additions"/> the ſame chapiter:<note place="margin">Ioh. vi.</note> Euerye manne (ſaith he) that hath hard &amp; learned of my father, commeth vnto me. Wherby we do learn, that except God doth teach vs inwardly, and geue vs grace to receiue his word, when it is preached vnto vs, all the preaching in the worlde canne profit vs nothing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHI.</speaker>
               <p>Then ye may ſe, how well y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame text of the reuelatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Ihon, dyth ſerue for theyr purpoſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EV.</speaker>
               <p>It ſerueth for their purpoſe, as al other authorityes and textes do, that they do aledge. For, in all thys matter, they worke by likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hodes. For why? in al the canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal bokes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture, they haue not one expreſſe woorde, whereby they canne proue that manne hath free will, or that he is able of hys owne ſtrength, to thinke or do any thing that good is.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DIDY.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiectiō </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. xix.</note>No? why doth Chriſte ſay then, if thou wilte enter into lyfe, kepe the commaundements?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1437:62" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <speaker>PHI.</speaker>
               <p>Ye haue neuer don. Nothing as I perceiue, can co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent you. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label> For if ye had well marcked, what was ſayd before, ye might haue percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it can not be proued by ſuch places that man hath free wyll, or that he is able of his own ſtrength to fulfyll the lawe and commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of God, wyth ſuche per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection as he dothe requyre. For, then we ſhoulde haue no neade of Chriſt,<note place="margin">gala. ii.</note> as Saint Paule dothe te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify, ſaying: If rightouſnes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth by the law, then Chriſt dyed in vain. But becauſe that ye ſhall not thinck, that I wil go about the buſh with you: ye ſhal vnderſtand, that Chriſt did attemperat &amp; order his anſwers according to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he did talke withal.<note place="margin">How the aunſwer of Chriſt made vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the yong man ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght to be taken and vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</note> A yong ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had aſked him, by what meane he might obtain life euerlaſting, &amp; what good he ſhuld do for to come by it? This yong perſon was puft vp with a vain perſwaſyon of the righteouſneſſe of the lawe, and
<pb facs="tcp:1437:63" rendition="simple:additions"/> alſo blineded with a foliſhe confy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and truſt, that he had in hys owne workes. Againe, he did aſke whiche were the deedes of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe wherby eternall felicity, and ſaluation myght be obteined? Therfore, he is by good right ſent vnto the law, whiche is a perfecte loking glaſſe or mirroure of rygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and alſo whiche muſte be fulfilled, if we wyll obtayn the rewarde of life euerlaſtinge. But who is able to fulfil it? No manne liuing, Chriſt onlye beinge excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Wherby it followeth that all they, that go aboute to be ſaued by the works of the law, are fartheſt of from ſaluation. The meaninge then of our ſauiour Ieſu Chriſt is that who ſo euer wyll be ſaued by workes, he muſte obſerue &amp; keepe the commaundements, wyth ſuch a perfection as God doth requyre, elſſe he can not enter into lyfe euer laſting, ſo that the yong man per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing his lacke and vnableneſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:1437:63"/> and how farre of he was from the perfection that he thoughte hym ſelfe to be in, mighte take an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon to ſeeke for the true and only remeady, that our moſt mercyfull father hathe appoynted for vs, to be ſaued by, and for to be delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the malediction &amp; curſe of the lawe, that al menne,<note place="margin">Gala. iii.</note> for lacke of fulfyllynge of the ſame, are ſubiecte vnto by theyr owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>Saye what ye wyll, my faythfull guydes dyd tell me, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiectiō </seg>
                  </label> that it is a playne hereſye, yea and a mooſte deteſtable blaſphemye to ſay that a man is not able to kepe the law and commaundementes, wyth ſuch a perfection as GOD doth requyre. For, if God ſhoulde commaund thinges impoſſible, he ſhoulde not be righteous. And by the lawe of nature, whyche by the finger of God, is wrytten in the hartes of men, we be not bounde to thinges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he impoſſyble, or that
<pb facs="tcp:1437:64"/> it lyeth not in oure power to ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyl.<note place="margin">Li. ii. de peccato et merit. et remi. cap. vi.</note> Saint Auguſtin dothe alſo te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify, that no man dothe ſin in that thing, that he is not able to ſhonne or auoid. Again, he wryteth thus: I can not thinke, that god did com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maund any thing that is impoſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,<note place="margin">Iero. ad damaſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> papam de ſimbobo fidei.</note> or that it is impoſſible vnto God to help to do that thyng, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che he hath commaunded. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they haue alleadged ſ. Ierome vnto me, ſaying we do curſe &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt the blaſphemy of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſaye, that God hath commaunded man to do any thing that is impoſſible, and that the commaundements of god can not be kept. They did alſo bring in Chriſoſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wher he ſaith: let vs not thinke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes of God be impoſſyble.<note place="margin">Hom. viii in mat.</note> For, truely they be bothe profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto vs and alſo very eaſye, if we wyll be dilygente or take good heede. And vnto this do the ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures agree. For, after that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes had publyſhed the law, he dyd
<pb facs="tcp:1437:64"/> ſay vnto the children of Iſrael: the commaundement,<note place="margin">Deu. xxx.</note> whiche I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund thee this daye, is not hyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den from the, neyther to farre, nor yet in heauen: but it is very nygh vnto thee, euen in thy mouth, and in thine harte that thou maiſt doe it.</p>
               <p>Again, Chriſt him ſelfe dothe ſay:<note place="margin">Mat. xi.</note> My yoke is eaſy, and my burde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is lyght. Moreouer theſe be the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the bleſſed Euangeliſte S. Ihon: for, this is the loue of God, that we keepe hys commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments:<note place="margin">i. Epi. v.</note> and his commaundements are not greuous or heauye. Theſe places do ſufficiently declare, that man is able to fulfil the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>As touching the fyrſte ſayinges of your fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full guydes, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label> wherein they doe affyrme and ſaye, that manne is able to fulfyll the lawe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes of God, we muſte vſe a diſtinction, that ſo we maye
<pb facs="tcp:1437:65"/> vphold and maintaine the veritye and truth of Goddes word. For, if they vnderſtande it of a man, that is graffed, or that hath fellowſhyp with Chriſt, I ſaye, that the ſame manne doth obſerue and kepe the hole law of God,<note place="margin">How the man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge rege<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nerated doth kepe the whole lawe of God.</note> not really in him ſelf, but becauſe that he is conduc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and led by the ſpirite of God. And alſo we may right well ſay, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he doth kepe the hole law of god, by the vertue of the fellowſhyppe that he hath with Chriſt, wherby he is made partaker, or rather put in full poſſeſſion of the perfect and conſummate obedience,<note place="margin">Rom. x.</note> and that oure ſauioure Ieſus Chriſte dyd ſhewe and yelde vnto God hys fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:<note place="margin">Retract. xix.</note> ſo that hys fautes ſhall not be imputed vnto him. For, Ieſus Chriſt doth ſupply whatſoeuer is lacking or wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting in ſuch a man. And ſo it may be true, that a man is able to kepe the lawe of God, in Ieſu Chriſt, and by Ieſu Chriſte, but not of hym ſelf. For, as Saynt
<pb facs="tcp:1437:65"/> Auguſtine ſaith: al the commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of god be fulfylled, when the ſynnes and fawtes be not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted. But if they wyll ſaye, that a manne beynge ſeparated from chriſt, is able to kepe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of god they ar in a great eror. For, chriſt him ſelfe ſayeth, that a tree canne bringe fourth no good fruyte,<note place="margin">Mat. vii.</note> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte it be made good fyrſt. But no man is good of his owne ſelfe, as it hathe bene declared alredye: Therfore, he can not bring fourth good fruite. Againe, theſe be the wordes of our ſauiour Ieſu Chriſt Byde in me, and I in you.<note place="margin">Ioh. xv.</note> As the braunche can not beare fruyte of it ſelfe, excepte it byde in the vine: no more canne ye, excepte ye abide in me, Ye ſee that oure ſauioure Ieſu Chriſte dothe ſhewe by thys ſimylitude, that it lyethe not in mannes power, to brynge anye good fruyte of hym ſelfe, excepte he be graffed in Chriſte.</p>
               <p>If ye haue well marked, what
<pb facs="tcp:1437:66" rendition="simple:additions"/> hath ben ſayd afore of fre wyl, ye ſhall well perceaue that it is ſo farre of, that manne of hym ſelfe, and by his owne ſtrengthe is able to fulfyll the lawe perfectely, that he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not wel vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, one only poynte of it, as it ought to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanded. For, ye muſt note that the lawe muſt be throughly obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and kepte wyth a pure and cleane heart,<note place="margin">Ro. vii.</note> as Saint Paule ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: The lawe is ſpirituall, but manne of him ſelf is polluted, and carnall, whyche thinge he confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth of him ſelfe, ſayinge: And I am carnall, ſolde vnder ſynne. How canne the lawe then, that is ſpirituall, and man whiche is carnall and fleſhely, agree? More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, the lawe wyll be kepte, euen from the conception of man, vnto the laſte daye and houre of of hys lyfe, wythoute anye ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of tranſgreſſyon or offence. For,<note place="margin">Iam. ii.</note> as Saynte Iames ſayeth:
<pb facs="tcp:1437:66"/> he that fawtethe or offendeth in one, is gylty of the whole. Item, the Lorde hym ſelfe ſayeth, that curſed are all menne,<note place="margin">De. xxvii</note> that do not abyde in al thyngs, that be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the booke of thys lawe, for to do them. How is manne able then to kepe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hole law of God, as it oughte to be kepte, and wyth ſuche a perfection as God dothe requyre, ſyth that he is a tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſour of it, afore he come in to thys worlde, and a ſynner from his conception? dothe not Dauyd wryte thus: My mother hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaned me in ſynne?<note place="margin">Pſal. ii.</note> I ſaye vnto you, that excepte manne be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued of the holye ghoſte, he ſhall neuer be able to kepe the whole lawe of God, as he doth wyl and requyre.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>Nowe truly I do per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue in deede, that it is a greate blaſphemye agaynſt Chriſt, to ſaye that man is able to fulfyll the hole lawe of God, of hys owne ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:1437:67"/> and by his owne ſtrengthe, and to do it with ſuch a perfection as god doothe requyre. For that were to ſay, that man is conceyued of the holye ghoſt. But I pray you, now tell me, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion </seg>
                  </label> whether God be vnrygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous or not in commaundynge man to do that thing, whiche he is not able to do, and fulfil?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label> What error or blaſphemy were it to ſaye ſo? I aſke you,<note place="margin">Simili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude</note> if a man wer bound vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you in a hundreth pounde, and dyd owe you them in dede: though the ſame manne were not able to pai you, ſhuld ye do vniuſtly to aſk him your C. pounde?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>No manne, I trowe, would ſay, that I did him wronge in aſking him my duety.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>When the kyng did aſke of his ſeruaunte the ten thouſand talentes,<note place="margin">Mat. xviii</note> that he dyd owe vnto him, did he vniuſtlye or wrongfullye?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>I wyl not ſay ſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1437:67" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <speaker>PHILALE.</speaker>
               <p>Know ye then, that all the hole law of God, is nothing els but a commaundement, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are commaunded and bidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to pay that vnto god, that we owe vnto hym. For man is bounde of duetye to loue God wyth all hys hart, wyth all hys ſoule, and with all his ſtrength: and his neighbor as hys owne ſelf.</p>
               <p>Therefore, Sainte Paule ſaythe:<note place="margin">Ro. viii.</note> brethren, we are debtours, but not vnto the fleſh. Shall we ſaye then that God is vnryghteous, or that he doth vniuſtly, aſking that thing of vs, that we do owe vnto hym of bound duety? It is ſo farre of, that he ſhould do vniuſtly in aſkynge vs of his duety,<note place="margin">Why god dothe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde of vs his dutye.</note> that rather he doth moſt iuſtly, godly, and ryghteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to demaund ſuch thynges of vs for the cauſes that I wyll now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe and aledge.</p>
               <p>Fyrſte and foremoſte, he doth it for to declare vnto men hys rygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:1437:68" rendition="simple:additions"/> holyneſſe, and bountu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe. For, in this that God doth commaund vs nothing in his lawe but that, whych is iuſte and good, he dothe declare therby that he him ſelf is righteous, holye and good. Secondly, leaſt men ſhoulde ſeke and go aboute to excuſe them ſelues by ignoraunce, before the iudgemente ſeate of God, ſayinge that they knewe not hys wyll and pleaſure, therfore dyd he ſetforthe hys law and commaundementes, for to declare vnto men, what he wyll haue them to do, and what he wyll haue them to leaue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done. For, we are ſuch, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we wold ſtyll plaid ignoraunce before God except we were conuicted by hys playne and manifeſt lawe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe commaundementes, that he hathe lefte vnto vs. Thirdlye, the law was geuen becauſe of tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion,<note place="margin">gala. iii.</note> to the intent that they, that wold not for the fear of God, and loue of heauenly thynges, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraine
<pb facs="tcp:1437:68" rendition="simple:additions"/> from doinge of euill, ſhould at leaſt for fear of the punyſhment of the lawe, be dryuen to keepe a good order, and to lyue quietlye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them ſelues. Els they wold haue kylled one an other, no man hadde bene able to haue kepte hys owne, but all ſhould haue gone to hauock. Forthly, God did ſetforth his law, that by it man ſhoulde be brought into the knowledge of his owne ſelf. That is to ſay,<note place="margin">The law is a mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour or lookinge glaſſe.</note> the law was geuen and ſetforthe to thys end, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it might be a lokinge glaſſe or mirrour, wherein man ſhoulde behold hys owne weakeneſſe, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becilitye and vnableneſſe to fulfil and perfourme the thynges that God dothe require of him, that ſo he may haue an occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to humble and ſubmit hym ſelf.</p>
               <p>For, if it were not for the law, that doothe dyſcouer, open and ſhewe, yea and ſet before our eies our owne filthyneſſe &amp; abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, we wold neuer acknowledge
<pb facs="tcp:1437:69" rendition="simple:additions"/> oure ſelues to bee ſinners, nor yet thyncke, that we haue nead of the grace and mercy of God. God ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore, leaſt men ſhould ſwel againſt hym, dothe demaunde and aſk the ſame of them, that they owe vnto him of duety. As if he ſhoulde ſaye by his law:</p>
               <p>O man, thou ſeeſt howe muche bound thou art vnto me,<note place="margin">Marke this dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentely</note> and how that thou art not able to paye the tenth part of that, which thou doſt owe vnto me, therfore, ſubmit thy ſelfe and acknowledge thine own imbecillity and weakeneſſe, and ſo flye vnto my mercy, whyche is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies prepared for them, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge of no reputation wyth them ſelues, do hang al together of me. And here may be gathered the fift cauſe,<note place="margin">Gala. iii.</note> whye the lawe was geuen: which is, that it myghte ſerue vs for a ſchole mayſter, for to brynge vs vnto Chriſte,<note place="margin">Rom. x.</note> who is the end or perfourming of the law, for to iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify
<pb facs="tcp:1437:69" rendition="simple:additions"/> al them, that do beleue.</p>
               <p>For, when we haue once learned by the Doctryne of the lawe, that of oure ſelues wee bee not able to eſcape the da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pnation, that we do deſerue by the breakyng of the commaundementes of God, then are we fayne to put awaye all vayne confydence and truſte, that we had in our own ſtrength, and in our owne merytes, and to flye vnto Chriſte, who was made accurſed for vs, that is to ſay, was punyſhed and ſlayne moſte oppro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pryouſlye for oure ſakes, that wee myght be delyuered from the curſe of the law, and ſo receyue the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge of Abraham, and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſe of the ſpirit through faithe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRAPE.</speaker>
               <p>I perceaue that god doth by his lawe,<note place="margin">Simili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</note> as a good ſchole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter is wonte to doe, when he hath a ſcholer, that for a lytle lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that he hathe, thincketh hym ſelf to know as much, as hys ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter doth. And therfore doth ſwell
<pb facs="tcp:1437:70"/> againſt his maſter, and beginneth to deſpiſe him. Nowe, when the maſter ſeeth that, he geueth vnto the ſame ſcholer, ſom difficult and hard leſſon, wherin he vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth nothing, or wherein he is as blinde as a beatell, and thys dothe he, that the ſcholer maye acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the ignoraunce that is hyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in him, vnder ſuch vain arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy and pryde. Euen ſo is it of man. For, excepte God, ſhoulde geue hym Commaundementes, whyche he is not hable to fulfyll, he would compte hym ſelfe as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye and as perfecte as God is: yea, he woulde ſaye playnelye, that he hadde no neade of God, nor of hys healpe.</p>
               <p>But God, for to ſtop all mennes mouthes, he geueth them a leſſon, wherein they be as blinde as bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, that ſo they maye be dryuen to knowe them ſelues, and to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge theyr owne infirmity and weakeneſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1437:70" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>Saint Augu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtine ſpeaketh of thys matter very godly, ſaying:<note place="margin">ad hilari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o. lxxxix.</note> 
                  <hi>Iubet lex vt iuſſa facere conati, et in noſtra infirmitate ſub lege fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigati, adiutorium gratiae poſcere noueri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus:</hi> that is to ſay: The lawe dothe commaund, that goyng aboute to keepe thoſe thinges that be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded and beinge wearied vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the law in oure infirmity and weakeneſſe, we may learne to call for the help of grace. And wryting vnto Aſellius, he ſaithe plainelye theſe wordes: <hi>Vtilitas legis eſt, vt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minem de ſua infirmitate conuincat, et gratiae medicinam,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">ad aſelliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> epiſto. C.</note> 
                  <hi>quae in Chriſto eſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorare compellat.</hi> This is (ſaith he) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vtility and profit of the lawe, that it may make man to know his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uict him of his weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſo compell hym to ſeeke for the ſalue and medicin of grace, whyche is in Chriſte. And in an other place he ſaythe: <hi>Iubet deus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">ad valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinum. epi. xcix.</note> 
                  <hi>quae non poſſumus, vt nouerimus quid ab illo petere debeamus.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1437:71" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>God dothe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund thoſe thinges that we be not able to do, that we maye learne, what we oughte to aſke of him. Again: The law was geuen,<note place="margin">Pſal. lxx.</note> to condempn you, and that beyng condempned, ye ſhould feat and that beynge afrayde, ye ſhuld craue for mercy, hauinge no truſte in your owne ſtrength. Moreouer vppon the hundreth and eightene Pſalme,<note place="margin">Pſ, exviii</note> and two and twenty ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon he wryteth thus: The lawe was geuen for this purpoſe, that it ſhould make thee of a high min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded perſone, lowlye and humble, and that it ſhould ſhew vnto thee, that thou haſt not of thyne owne, ſtrength vnto righteouſneſſe: that ſo being poore, bare, &amp; naked thou ſhouldeſt flye vnto grace. And then turning him ſelf vnto god, he ſaith So do, O Lord, ſo do, O mercyful Lord, commaund that thinge that can not be fulfilled: yea commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that thinge, that can not be fulfyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led but throughe thy grace, that
<pb facs="tcp:1437:71" rendition="simple:additions"/> when men ſhall not be able to ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyl it by theyr owne ſtrengthe, all mouthes maye be ſtopped, and no man ſhould ſeme vnto hym ſelfe to be high. Let all men be litle ones, humble and lowli: let al the world be ſubiect vnto God. Manye other places might I aledge oute of the ſame doctoure, but theſe ſhal now ſuffiſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe be goodly ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges, and worthye to be marcked. I could hear no ſuch things of my faithfull guides.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRAPELVS.</speaker>
               <p>No I warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t you. For al that they go aboute,<note place="margin">Why the enemyes of the tru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>the got a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute to vrge the doctrin of the lawe.</note> is by the doctrine of the lawe, eyther to dryue menne vnto deſperation, or elſſe to pufte them vppe with a vayn confidence and truſt of their owne ſtrength and merites.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>Nowe do I perceiue that it is ſo. And I am aſhamed that I dyd geue ſo ſone creadyte vnto them.</p>
               <p>But I pray you, brother Phila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lethes,
<pb facs="tcp:1437:72" rendition="simple:additions"/> tell me, how the ſame ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of ſaint Auguſtine oughte to be vnderſtanded, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion </seg>
                  </label> where he ſayeth: No man doth ſynne in that thing, that he is not able to ſhunne or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyde. For, ſome might gather by the ſame ſayinge, that if it were impoſſible for me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to kepe the lawe they ſhould not offend nor yet ſyn in doynge againſte the lawe, nor in being diſobedient vnto god, ſith that they could do non otherwyſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALE.</speaker>
               <p>Ye ſhall vnderſtand that there Saint Auguſtine dothe ſpeake of thoſe thinges, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <note place="margin">How. S. Auguſtin ought to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanded.</note> that man is naturally ſubiect vnto from his own byrth, as is: colde, heate, hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, thirſt, &amp; ſlepe with ſuch other like, which we maye well call hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne infirmyties. His meaning then is, that man dothe not ſyn in doinge thoſe thingss for the ſuſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce and preſeruation of hys life, whyche he is not able to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare. As, if a manne doth warm hym ſelfe, when hee is a colde,
<pb facs="tcp:1437:72"/> or doth eate when he is a hungred and ſo fourth. If a man then doth, eat, drink, warm him ſelf &amp; ſlepe, when neede dothe require, he ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not. For, why? he can not lyue wythout ſuche thinges. So both Saint Auguſtine doth vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande it. Who dothe alſo procede &amp; go farther, vnderſtandinge the ſame of Adam before his fal. For, if it had not lien in hym to wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the temptation of the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhoulde not haue ſynned. But ſyth that he coulde haue reſiſted, if he hadde would, and dyd not, ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore is he wyth all hys ſede, found gylty. And becauſe that he did not vſe well the ſtrengthe, that was geuen hym, therefore, was it iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye taken awaye from hym, and from all hys poſterity. No manne then ought to ſay, that Adam and his ſede do not ſynne, in doynge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the lawe of God, ſythe that they theyr ſelues are cauſe of their vnableneſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1437:73"/>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>This I do well vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiectiō </seg>
                  </label> But yet I can not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue, but that the places of the ſcripture, whyche they aleaged do make againſt you altogether: For Moſes ſayeth: The commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente,<note place="margin">Deu. xxx.</note> which I commaunde thee this day, is not hydden from thee, neither far of, nor yet in heauen, but it is nyghe vnto thee, euen in thy mouth, and in thine harte that thou maiſt doe it. Chriſt him ſelfe who is the true expoſitoure of the lawe and of Moſes ſaieth alſo?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. xi.</note>My yoke is eaſy, and my burde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is lyght. And the holye ghoſt by the bleſſed Euangeliſte S. Ihon, doth plainely ſpeake theſe words. This is the loue of God, that we kepe hys commaundementes:<note place="margin">1. Epiſt. v</note> and his commaundements are not heauy. Who woulde not iudge by this that it lyethe in mannes power to kepe the commaundementes of God?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DIDYMVS.</speaker>
               <p>I cunne you thanke,
<pb facs="tcp:1437:73"/> brother Albion, I thought, that ye wold haue forgotten thoſe places how be it I wold not ſuffred them to be paſt ouer ſo lyghtlye. For, there be manye,<note place="margin">The free wyl men.</note> euen among them that be fauourers, or at leſt, wyll ſeme to be fauourers of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, that haue alwayes theſe au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toryties in theyr mouthes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>That is not vnknowen vnto me, and therfore, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label> I am gladde that they haue bene ſetfourthe, that by the ryghte ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundinge of them, we maye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuer thoſe perſons from the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, that they be in, or if they wyl not, at leaſt we may warne other, that they fall not in to it. As for the place of deuteronomi it is moſt playn,<note place="margin">How the place of Moſes ou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ght to be vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</note> that Moſes doth not ſpeake there of the bare commaundemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, nor yet of any eaſyneſſe, that is in the kepynge of them (Some in deede doe vnderſtande it of the facillity and eaſynes that is in the knowing and learning of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) but
<pb facs="tcp:1437:74"/> of the couenaunte of mercy, which he had both comprehended and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blyſhed wyth the lawe. For, he had taughte a lyttle before, that oure heartes muſte be circumciſed wyth the hande of God, els we could not loue hym, he doth not then, put the ſame facility and eaſineſſe, whiche whiche he doth ſpeake of there, in the vertue and ſtrength of man, but in the helpe and ayde of the holye ghoſt, whiche worketh mightelye his worke, in oure infyrmitye and weakeneſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For if Moſes, had ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken there of the bare commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes onlye he ſhoulde haue puft vp the people with a moſt hurtfull and pernitious confydence, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they muſt nedes to haue caſte them ſelues headlonge in to vtter deſtruction, if they had attempted to obſerue and kepe the lawe, by theyr owne ſtrengthe.</p>
               <p>For, when they hadde felt them ſelues vnable to doo it, woulde they not haue taken to playne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperation: if they hadde knowen
<pb facs="tcp:1437:74" rendition="simple:additions"/> none other waye or meane for to obtayne ſaluation, and to eſcape death, but by the perfecte kepinge of the lawe? Sainte Paul then ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing then a perfect vnderſtanding of this place, doth applye it alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether vnto the doctrine of fayth. For, hauinge ſpoken of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe that cometh by the lawe, and how that they that obſerue and kepe the commaundementes ſhal lyue by them, he doth adde im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatelye theſe wordes: But the righteouſneſſe that cometh of faith ſpeaketh on this wyſe:<note place="margin">Rom. x.</note> Saye not in thy hearte: Who ſhall aſcende in to heauen? For that were to fetch Chriſt downe: Or who ſhall go down in to the depe? For that wer to fetch vp Chriſt from death. But what ſayethe the ſcripture? The worde is nyghe thee, euen in thy mouth, and in thy hearte.</p>
               <p>This is the worde of fayth, which we preache.</p>
               <p>If thou ſhalt confeſſe or knowledge wyth thy mouth that Ieſus is the
<pb facs="tcp:1437:75"/> Lorde: and ſhalt beleue wyth thy hart, that God rayſed him vp from death, thou ſhalt be ſafe. For, the belyef of the heart iuſtifyeth, and the confeſſion of the mouth maketh man ſafe. Who would requyre a more ſounde expoſition of Moſes wordes than this is?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>This expoſition can in no wyſe miſlyke me, ſyth that it cometh from the ſame ſelfe ſpirit, that Moſes did writ by. Nowe, therefore, come to the ſayinges of Chriſt, and of Iohn the euangeliſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALE.</speaker>
               <p>Such ſayinges are moſte true, as it dothe appeare by that,<note place="margin">How the ſayinges of Chriſt and Iohn the eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liſt ought to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded</note> which hath ben ſayed before. For, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundements of god, of them ſelues are eaſy, and if there be any dyfficultye or hardneſſe in them: it cometh not of the nature and propertye of the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of God, but of the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of manne. Heare, what Saint Paule ſayethe: what ſo euer the lawe coulde not fulfyll,<note place="margin">Ro. viii.</note> in
<pb facs="tcp:1437:75" rendition="simple:additions"/> as much as it was weake becauſe of the fleſh, that ſame did God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourme, ſendinge his ſonne in the ſimilitude of ſynneful fleſh, and by ſynne damned ſinne.<note place="margin">Two thinges to be lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned in Pauls ſayinge.</note> Two things do we learne in thys ſaying of the Apoſtle: Fyrſte, that it commeth not of the law, that menne are not able to fulfil it, but of the imbecili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and weakneſſe of the fleſh. The lawe then, and the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes be eaſy, and if ther be any difficultye or hardneſſe in the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of them, it commeth of our naughty and corrupted nature.</p>
               <p>Secondly we do learn, that God dothe by his ſonne Ieſu Chriſte, ſupply the ſame, that by reaſon of the weakeneſſe of our fleſh, we be not able to fulfyl. Again: the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements of god are eaſy and lyght vnto hym, that is graffed in Chriſt, and that hathe fellowſhyp wyth him. For, thoſe thyngs that afore were harde vnto manne, are made eaſy vnto him bi faith, wher
<pb facs="tcp:1437:76" rendition="simple:additions"/> by he is graffed in Chriſt, as ſaint Paule doth teſtify, ſaying: I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to do all thinges through him, that doth comforte me. And ſo the ſaying of S. Auguſtin ſhalbe true where he ſayth: I can not thincke, that God hath commaunded anye thing that is impoſſible.<note place="margin">Phi. iiii.</note> Elſſe S. Auguſtine doth graunte in many other places, that God hathe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded thinges, that it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſible for man to fulfyll, as in the boke of the ſpirit, and of the letter, and in his thyrde treatyſe vppon Ihon. And ſo ought al to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtanded,<note place="margin">How Chriſoſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanded.</note> that they aleadge, bothe oute of Chriſoſtome, &amp; of Ierome, that is to ſaye, that the commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes of God, were eaſye to kepe. For, the faithful man is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded &amp; dothe beleue, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is wanting or lackynge in him, the ſame is ſupplied by chriſt with whome he hath felowſhyppe through faith. Whyche working through chariti &amp; loue, cauſeth the
<pb facs="tcp:1437:76" rendition="simple:additions"/> commaundements of god to be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy vnto the inner man, whyche is borne of newe, or which is renued by the holy ghoſt, God hauynge a chief reſpect vnto the wyll and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, that ſuch a man hath to kepe them actually, if it dyd lye in hys power, and wherby he doth ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor him ſelf daily to fulfill them. For, it is the duety of him that is renued,<note place="margin">What is the duety of him that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed.</note> to ſtudy daily and hourly to kepe the commaundementes of god, though he be not able by him ſelf, and of hys owne ſtrength, to attain to the perfect keping of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For we muſt not, becauſe that we are not able to kepe the law of god as it ought to be kept, be ſlack ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore to do that, whiche lieth in vs, beinge ſure that oure obedience, though it be vnperfect, ſhalbe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted before God, as longe as we be true members of hys ſonne Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu Chriſte.<note place="margin">Why the auncient fathers ſpake as they did.</note> For thys cauſe did the auncyent doctours ſpeake as they dyd, that ſo they myght take away<pb facs="tcp:1437:77"/> from men, the vaine excuſes, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che they be wont to make becauſe of the impoſſibility of the law.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DIDyMVS.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhe and found ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</note>I was once in a place where I hard a ſtout champion of the Romiſh church ſay, that there haue bene, not one nor two, but many, that dyd beſydes Chriſt, ful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyll the law of God, wyth a moſte conſummate perfection, as Ioſua, and zacharie Ihons father, ſaying that this is wrytten of Ioſua: As the Lorde commaunded hys ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunte Moſes, and as Moſes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded Ioſua,<note place="margin">Ioſu. xi.</note> euen ſo did Ioſua ſo that there was nothing vndone at al of thoſe things that god com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded Moſes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>I aſke you: whether was Ioſua a man, that was conceiued after the common ſort of other men or not?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DIDyMVS.</speaker>
               <p>I beleue that he was a man, and that he was conceiued betwixt man and woman as other men are.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1437:77"/>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>Ye beleue wel: for, it is ſo in dede. We muſte then confeſſe and graunt that Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſua did go a ſtray from the law of God, that he was a lyer, and that he was filled wyth manye myſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes. For, it is ſayd of all menne,<note place="margin">Ro. iii.</note> that be borne of man and woman, that they haue all gone oute of the waye, &amp; that they be alſo al lyers:<note place="margin">Pſal. cxvi</note> howe dare then youre bragginge marchauntes, be ſo bold to affirm, that Ioſua hath kept the hole law of God. For, theſe be two contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry things: to be a lyer, and to haue kept the law of God perfectlye. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: I woulde fayne knowe of you, whether Ihon Baptyſte, or Ihon the Euangeliſt, was not as perfect as Ioſua? Or whether Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſua was more perfecte, than anye of thoſe two, that I named euen now?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DYDIMVS.</speaker>
               <p>I beleue, that Ioſua was not more perfecte, than they were.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1437:78" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <speaker>PHILALE.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. iii.</note>Heare then, what Ihon Baptiſt did ſay vnto our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Ieſu Chriſte, when he came vnto him for to be baptiſed: I haue nead to be baptiſed of thee, &amp; doſte thou come vnto me? Sythe then, that S. Ihon doth confeſſe that he had neade to be baptiſed, it was a token, that he was infected wyth ſynne. And wherof doth come the ſame infection of ſynne, but of the tranſgreſſion of the law? We can not deny then, but that Ihon was a tranſgreſſor of the law, and that therfore (if theyr opinion be true) Ioſua was more perfecte than he.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DyDIMVS.</speaker>
               <p>I cannot beleue that Ioſua was more perfect than Iho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Baptiſt. For, it is ſaid of him, that amonge all thoſe,<note place="margin">Mat. xi.</note> that be borne of a woman, there aroſe no greater than he was.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>Ye muſte then confeſſe that Ioſua was a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: if he was a ſinner, then did he offend againſt the lawe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1437:78"/>
               <speaker>DIDyMVS.</speaker>
               <p>I canne not ſaye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>Heare alſo what the bleſſed Euangeliſt ſaint Ihon doth ſay: if we ſaye,<note place="margin">i. epi. i.</note> that we haue no ſinne, we deceaue our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, and the truthe is not in vs. I am ſure that Ioſua, was not more perfect than the bleſſed Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geliſt Sainte Ihon was, who, as ye ſee, doth put hym ſelfe in the number of ſynners.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DIDyMVS.</speaker>
               <p>I would fain learn, howe the ſame that is wrytten of Ioſua, muſte bee vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. For, it is ſayde plainelye, that he lefte none of thoſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges vndone, that Moſes commaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>Ye muſte marke,<note place="margin">How that whiche was ſaied of Ioſua ought to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanded.</note> that the ſame place muſte bee vnderſtanded of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes, that Moſes dyd geue vnto Ioſua, touchynge the
<pb facs="tcp:1437:79" rendition="simple:additions"/> gouernment of the people, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo touchinge the brynginge of the children of Iſraell into the land of Canaam, and not of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moral law, that is wrytten in the two tables of ſtone. For, the ſame lawe was not geuen particularlye vnto Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſua, but vnto all the people in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral. That ſame place the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, muſt be vnderſtanded of the commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes, that Moſes did geue vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to Ioſua, concerning the gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and guidinge of the people, whyche he dyd fulfyl to the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DyDIMVS.</speaker>
               <p>And what ſaye ye of zacharie the father of Ihon Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt,<note place="margin">Luc. i.</note> and of hys mother? For, it is wrytten of them, that they were both ryghteous before God, &amp; that they walked in all the commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements and ſtatutes of the Lord, vnreprouable.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILA.</speaker>
               <p>What ſay ye, neighbor Dydimus, was not zacharie a prieſt, which did execute his offyce
<pb facs="tcp:1437:79" rendition="simple:additions"/> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, when his curſe came, accordynge to the cuſtome of the prieſthode?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DIDyMVS.</speaker>
               <p>Yes verely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>Then was he a ſynner, and was fayne to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſacrifyce fyrſte for hys owne ſynnes,<note place="margin">Heb. vii.</note> and then for the ſynnes of the people. For, thus it is wryt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: It became vs to haue ſuche an hie prieſt, as is holy, innocent, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled, ſeparated from ſynners, &amp; made higher then heauen, whiche neadeth not daily, as yonder high prieſtes, to offer vp ſacrifyce, fyrſte for hys owne ſinnes, and then for the ſynnes of the people. For that did he once for all, when he offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp hym ſelfe. Here haue we a notable difference betwixt Chriſt our ſouerain prieſt, and the hyghe prieſtes of the law. Fyrſt and fore moſt the high prieſtes of the lawe, were fain to offer ſacrifyces often becauſe that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrifices that they offered continually euerye yeare,
<pb facs="tcp:1437:80"/> coulde not make them, that came there vnto perfecte. But Chriſte wyth one only ſacrifyce,<note place="margin">Heb. x.</note> dyd make them perfect for euer that are ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified. Again, the highe prieſtes of the law, were fayne to offer ſacry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices. Fyrſt for theyr own ſinnes, and then for the ſynnes of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. For, thus ſayde Moſes vnto Aaron:<note place="margin">Leui. xvi.</note> goe vnto the aultare, and offer thy ſynne offrynge, and thy burnt offrynge, and make an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement for thee, and for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Then offer the peoples of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringe, and reconcile them alſo, as the Lord hath commaunded. But our ſauiour Ieſus Chriſte, who is oure ſoueraigne and euerlaſtynge prieſt, is holye, innocente, vndefy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, ſeparated from ſinners, andmade higher then heauen, ſo that he neaded not to offer for his own ſinnes, as the prieſtes of the olde law did.<note place="margin">i. epi. ii.</note> For, why? he neuer com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſinne, nor gile was founde in his mouthe: I am ſure that ye
<pb facs="tcp:1437:80" rendition="simple:additions"/> will not ſaye, that Zachary Ihon Baptiſtes father, was ſuch a one.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DYDIMVS.</speaker>
               <p>I wil not ſay ſo. For there is no man that ſynneth not.<note place="margin">i. king. viii. Rom. iii.</note> Againe: All men haue ſynned, and lacke the praiſe that is of valewe before God. Moreouer, we do rede that zachari was puniſhed, becauſe that he doubted of the promyſe of God,<note place="margin">Luc. i.</note> which was reueled vnto him by the aungell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALE.</speaker>
               <p>Ye maye perceyue then that he was called righteous not becauſe that he hadde fulfyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the lawe wyth ſuche a perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyon as GOD dothe requyre of vs,<note place="margin">Why za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chary was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led righte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous.</note> but becauſe that by the meare mercye and goodneſſe of almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye GOD, taken holde vppon by faythe, hys ſynnes were not imputed vnto hym, but was comp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted ryghteous before GOD,<note place="margin">Rom. iiii</note> as Abraham was, vnto whome hys faythe was imputed for ryghte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1437:81" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>And of this faithe did it come, that both he and his wife Elizabeth did endeuour them ſelues to walke ſo vprightly in the commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts and ſtatutes of the Lorde, that no manne ſhoulde be able to reproue them, or to lay any thing to theyr charge. In the meane whyle, they cried bothe vnto God, and ſayde: Enter not into iudgemente wyth thy ſeruauntes,<note place="margin">Pſal. cxlii</note> O Lorde, for in thy ſyghte no manne ſhall be iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DYDIMVS.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">iiii. kings xxiii. Obiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </note>Hee dyd alſo brynge in the example of Ioſias, of whome it is wrytten after thys manner: There was no kynge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, lyke vnto hym whych ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted vnto the Lord wythall hys harte, wythall hys ſoule, and with all his ſtrength: according to all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of Moſes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILA.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Aunſwer</note>I wyll haue none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but the words that ye haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged for to proue that Ioſias was a tranſgreſſoure of the lawe?
<pb facs="tcp:1437:81"/> For, it is writen of him, that there was no kynge before, which ſo conuerted or tourned him ſelfe vnto the Lord, as he did. But how coulde he conuert or returne vnto the Lord, except he had gon away from hym? And we go awaye from God throughe or by ſynne, whiche is a playne tranſgreſſion or brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge of the lawe: Therefore Ioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as was a tranſgreſſour of the law.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DIDYMVS.</speaker>
               <p>Yet it is written of him, that there was not hys lyke that did ſo conuert vnto the Lorde wyth all his harte, accordynge to all the lawe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALE.</speaker>
               <p>It foloweth not ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, becauſe it is ſayed that Ioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as obſerued and kept the law more diligentely than al the other kings that he did kepe it perfectlye. For, neither he,<note place="margin">How y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche is ſpoken of Ioſias ought to be taken.</note> nor any other beſydes dyd euer kepe it perfectlye.</p>
               <p>It is to be thoughte that Ioſyas hathe bene a greater zelatoure of the lawe of God than all the other
<pb facs="tcp:1437:82"/> were, yet it foloweth not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that he kepte the lawe wyth ſuch a perfection, as God dothe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyre.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DIDyMVS.</speaker>
               <p>What ſay ye, to theſe wordes of Dauid: <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiectiō </seg>
                  </label> I haue walked in all thy commaundementes, and haue hated all wicked wayes. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain: In thy teſtemonyes is my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyght, they are my counſeyllers? Myght not a man gether, by ſuche ſayings, that the holy prophet Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid kept the lawe, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes of God moſte per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectelye?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHSE.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Aunſwer </seg>
                  </label> If any man ſhould ſo do, he ſhoulde greatlye be deceaued. For, by ſuch words, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid doth only declare the great zele and good affection,<note place="margin">A declara<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of Dauids wordes.</note> that hee dyd beare vnto the law and commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of God, and the good eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, that he hadde of them. For, if he ſhoulde ſaye and boaſte, that he hadde kepte the lawe and commaundements of God perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye:
<pb facs="tcp:1437:82"/> the ſcripture ſhould proue him as lyar. For, it teſtifyeth and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth of hym, that he was bothe an aduouterer and a murtherer. But to ſaye that an aduouterer or murtherer hathe kept the lawe of God wyth ſuche a perfection,<note place="margin">ii. Samu. xi.xii.</note> as God doth requyre that wer a blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemye againſt God and againſt his lawe. Moreouer, after that he hadde committed ſuche deteſtable and enorme crymes, and hadde ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned forgeueneſſe and pardone for the ſame, dyd he not ſynne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne moſte greauouſlye agaynſt God,<note place="margin">ii. Samu. xxiiii.</note> when he did rekynne his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? Ye ſee then, how Dauyd did manye and ſondrye tymes offende againſt the lawe.</p>
               <p>Therefore,<note place="margin">Pſa. cxxx</note> dothe he crye oute ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge: If thou, Lorde, wylte be extreame to marke what is done amyſſe, oh Lorde, who maye abide it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DI.</speaker>
               <p>By our brother Albions leue I
<pb facs="tcp:1437:83"/> wyll brynge fourth all the ſayings of that moſt valyaunte champyon of the Romiſhe churche, ſyth that they ſerue ſo well for our purpoſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>ALBION.</speaker>
               <p>Ye ſhall haue good leaue of me, neighbour Didymus. For, through the occaſion of them, many goodly matters are diſcuſſed whiche (as ye ſayed before) ſerue verye well for this oure communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, that we haue now in hand. Therfore, go on in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DIDyMVS.</speaker>
               <p>He did in his greate heate affyrme moſt ſtoutely that a man was able to fulfyll theſe two co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundements:<note place="margin">The proud aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſercion of the papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes.</note> Thou ſhalt loue the Lorde thy god, with all thyne hearte, wyth al thy ſoule, and with all thy ſtrength. And thou ſhalt not couet.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>If ye wyll marke diligentely all, that hath bene ſayed afore,<note place="margin">Aunſwer vnto it.</note> ye ſhall ſoone perceaue, that it is impoſſible for any manne to do it.</p>
               <p>For, thys commaundemente:
<pb facs="tcp:1437:83"/> Thou ſhalt loue the Lord thy God wyth all thine harte, wyth all thy ſoule, and wythall thy ſtrengthe, doth require a moſte pure &amp; cleane hart, whiche ſhoulde be wythoute ſpot or blemiſh.<note place="margin">Pro. xx.</note> But who in al the hole world can truely ſaye: I haue a cleane hart?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DIDyMVS.</speaker>
               <p>I do wel vnderſtand all thys hole matter, God be pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and thanked for it. But I wyl only reherſe vnto you, the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication and talcke of thys noble and valiaunte knighte of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh beaſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRA.</speaker>
               <p>I praye you, brother Philalethes, that ye wyll geue me leaue to aunſwer a while, that ſo ye may haue ſome brething tyme. For, ſence ye came, ye neuer rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILALETHES.</speaker>
               <p>I am well content.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRAPELVS.</speaker>
               <p>Nowe then, neyghboure Dydimus, let vs hear all the wyſe talcke and communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
<pb facs="tcp:1437:84"/> of this noble knighte, and valiaunt champion of the Romiſh church.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DIDYMVS.</speaker>
               <p>He did ſaye, that by this Commaundemente. (Thou ſhalt loue the Lord thy God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all thine harte, with all thy ſoule, and wyth all thy ſtrengthe) is not required an actual loue or motion of the hart towards God, but that it is inough, if it be not interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by ſome deadlye ſinne: ſo that, he is compted to keepe thys com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, whyche preferreth nothing before God, nor wold for all the goodes and rycheſſe in the worlde, breake one of hys com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commaundements.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRAPELVS.</speaker>
               <p>Truelye this is a very ſubſtantiall diuinity, and worthye of ſuche an excellente de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine, as he thinketh him ſelf to be. How could it be, I praye you, that a man ſhoulde kepe him ſelfe from offending God, excepte he ſhoulde loue him actually, that is to ſay, in
<pb facs="tcp:1437:84"/> verye deede. For, all that is done,<note place="margin">If the harte of manne be voyde of the loue of god he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do no good.</note> without the loue of God, is ſinne. If the hart of man then, be voyde of the loue of God, what good can he do? I ſaye vnto you, that all the ſinnes that a man committeth, do come of this, that he loueth not God actually. Conſider &amp; marke, what the Lorde hym ſelfe ſaythe, ſpeakinge of his lawe. And thys ſhall be a ſigne vnto thee in thyne hande, and a token to thincke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon before thine eies,<note place="margin">Exo. xiii.</note> howe that the Lord brought vs out of Egipt wyth a mighty hande. And when the true and faythfull ſeruaunt of God Moſes, had ſaid:<note place="margin">Deu. vi.</note> Thou ſhalte loue the Lorde thy God wyth all thine heart. &amp;c. He did adde by and by: Theſe woordes, whych I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde thee thys daye, ſhalt thou laye vppe in thine hart, thou ſhalt rehearſe theym vnto thy Chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and ſhalt talcke of theym, when thou ſitteſt in thyne houſe?
<pb facs="tcp:1437:85"/> when thou walckeſt by the waye, when thou lyeſt downe, and when thou ryſeſt vppe. And in an other place, he wryteth on this manner: Take heede to thy ſelfe nowe,<note place="margin">Deu. iiii.</note> and kepe well thy ſoule, that thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get not the thynges, whych thyne eyes haue ſeene, and that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parte not out of thine heart, al the dayes of thy life. Ye ſee that God dothe require bothe an actuall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce of hys wonderous workes, and alſo an actuall loue towardes hym.<note place="margin">Ioh. xiiii.</note> Ieſus Chriſte alſo ſayeth: if ye loue me kepe my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. Again: This is the loue of God (ſaithe the bleſſed E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſt ſ. Iho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) that we keepe his commaundementes.<note place="margin">i. Ioh. v.</note> It followeth then that we muſte haue fyrſte, an actual loue of God in our hartes, if we wil keepe his lawe, or keepe our ſelues from falling into ſinne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DyDIMVS.</speaker>
               <p>Now do I perceiue, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the opinion of this maſter doctor is abhomynable, and diuelyſhe.
<pb facs="tcp:1437:85"/> Therfore, I do vtterlye forſake it, as moſt erroneous and heretical. But now, tel me, I pray you, how this commaundement: Thou ſhalt not couet, ought to be vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. For, this galant doctoure dyd ſay, that God dothe not forbyd the concupiſcence, but that he doth on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forbid &amp; condemne the agreinge vnto it, affirming ſtifly,<note place="margin">The opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the ſcole men tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cupiſence</note> that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence is no ſinne, excepte we do conſent and agree vnto it. For ſaithe he, the concupiſcences and luſtes of the fleſh, after baptiſme, be left vnto vs for an exercyſe of vertue, and for an occaſion to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and deſerue, that after we haue manfully foughten in this world, we maye in the other receyue the crown of glory, &amp; of righteouſnes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EV.</speaker>
               <p>By what authorityes of the ſcripture did he proue his ſaying?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DYDIMVS.</speaker>
               <p>By the ſaying of S. Auguſtine, wher he wryteth, that concupiſcence is no ſynne in them that bee regenerated or borne of
<pb facs="tcp:1437:86"/> new, excepte we conſente vnto the ſame wicked &amp; naughtye workes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EVTRA.</speaker>
               <p>This galant doctor of yours, doth great wrong to ſ. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin. For, he ſaith not only, that concupiſcence is no ſin, but that it is no ſinne in them, that are born of new, as ye your ſelf do wel per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue by his woordes that ye haue aleadged. For, god ſaith not: thou ſhalt not go after thy concupiſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: Thou ſhalt not bring them to effect, nor conſent vnto them: but he ſaithe plainlye: Thou ſhalt not couet. And that concupiſcence in them, that are born of new, is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for no ſinne, it commeth not of the concupiſcence, but of the newe byrthe or regeneration, whiche bryngeth to paſſe that God dothe not vnto hym that is borne of new impute hys concupyſcence for ſin. For, it is wrytten: he that is born of God,<note place="margin">i. Ioh. iii.</note> ſinneth not, that is to ſay: his ſin is not imputed vnto him. Againe, it is ſaide, that be ſynneth
<pb facs="tcp:1437:86"/> not: becauſe that he ſuffereth not ſynne to raigne in him. Moreouer I wyll proue by liuelye reaſons, that concupiſcence, that is to ſaye, all euyll motions of the harte are ſynne. Fyrſt and foremoſte I aſke of you: wherof commeth concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence? of the fleſhe or of the ſpirite?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DyDIMVS.</speaker>
               <p>I graunt, that it co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth of the fleſh.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EV.</speaker>
               <p>It followeth then that concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence is fleſhlye. For, as Chriſte ſaith. That which is born of fleſh,<note place="margin">Ioh. iii.</note> is fleſh.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DIDyMVS.</speaker>
               <p>I do confeſſe that to.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EV.</speaker>
               <p>It followeth then that concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence is ſynne. For, the fleſh in it ſelfe is nothyng elſſe but ſinne, euer repugnynge againſte the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, as it is wrytten: The fleſh co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueteth agaynſte the ſpirit. And in an other place, Saint Paule ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth alſo:<note place="margin">gala. v.</note> The workes of the fleſhe are manifeſt, which are whoredo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e, enuy, Idolatry. &amp;c.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:1437:87"/>
               <p>I aſke this of you: he that geueth occaſion of ſynne, is not he parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of the ſinne? He that biddeth to ſteale, and he that ſtealeth, be they not both theues? Now, it is ſo, that euery euel motion of the hart, doth ſtir vp man for to ſinne, and if ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth not aſſent nor agre vnto it, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faut and lacke, is not in the concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence, that dothe all that in it doth lie to caſt man headlong into ſinne, but it is the holy ghoſte that dothe mortifye the ſame concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence in them, that be regenerated or borne of newe. Seing then that all ſinnes do come and proceade of the concupiſcence, and euil motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the hart, we muſte neades con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that ſuche concupiſcence and euil motions of the hart, are euell. If they be euill, then are they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden of God. For, God doth not only commaunde to auoide ſinne, but alſo the occaſion of ſinne. Sith then that we do retein and kepe in vs, ſuch euil motions of the harte,
<pb facs="tcp:1437:87"/> we do euil. For, vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ye, that God by this commaundement. (Thou ſhalt not couet) dothe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne and forbid al euil concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence and naughty motions of the hart, and not onlye the frutes that ſpring therof. That is to ſaye: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that God wyll haue all oure whole ſoule to be filled and poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with the affectyon of loue and charity, hys wyll and pleaſure is, that we ſhould baniſh and caſt out of our harts al manner of things, that be contrary vnto charity and brotherly loue, ſo that no thought ſhoulde riſe in oure mindes, for to kindle our harts wyth any concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence, that might be hurtfull &amp; noyſome vnto our neighbor. For, it is the concupiſcence, that pryc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth and tickeleth the hart, for to in tice him to ſinne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DIDyMVS.</speaker>
               <p>It may be that man ſhall not conſent to it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EV.</speaker>
               <p>If man ſhould conſent vnto it, then the ſame conſent, ſhoulde no
<pb facs="tcp:1437:88"/> more be called concupiſcence only, but a deliberate purpoſe. And true<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, it is no meruel that God dothe requyre ſuch a perfection,<note place="margin">Why god doth require ſuch a per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fection and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightuee in man.</note> and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe in man. For, who wyll ſaye the contrarye, but that it is moſte ryghte, that all the powers of the ſoule oughte to be applyed and geuen to charity? And if anye part of the ſoule dothe ſhrincke or ſwarue from it, I mean, from the loue, that we owe vnto God, and our neighboure, al men muſt nead confeſſe that it is fauty &amp; nought. For, wherof dothe it come, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny deſire to hurt our neyghboure, entreth into our hart, but only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that deſpiſinge other, we do only ſeke our owne profit? For, if our whole hart wer fully poſſeſſed with charity and brotherlye loue, no ſuch imaginations ſhuld haue entraunce into it. Therefore, we muſte conclude, that the harte is void of charitye, for as muche as it doth conceiue ſuch concupiſcence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:1437:88"/>
               <speaker>DYDIMVS.</speaker>
               <p>But me thyncketh, that it is not meete and conueny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, that ſuch vayne fantaſyes, as do come into a mannes brayn, and afterwards do vaniſh away, ſhuld be taken and condemned for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcences, which properly haue their of ſpring in the hart.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>EV.</speaker>
               <p>I ſaye, that God by thys com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement. Thou ſhalt not co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uet, forbiddeth not only thoſe ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, that riſe in mans harte, but alſo, al vain thoughtes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> may by anye meane moue &amp; ſtir vp the hart vnto concupiſcence. For, we can neuer ſo ſone luſt or deſire any thing in our mind, but that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hart is ſtraightwais therwith touched and enflamed, whether it be lyttle or much. But the lord doth require of vs a moſt perfect charity, which ſhould be fartheſt from all fleſhlye concupiſcence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>PHILA.</speaker>
               <p>Sithens that thys matter, hathe bene ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fycyentlye debated, I thyncke it good, that heare we make an end,
<pb facs="tcp:1437:89" rendition="simple:additions"/> praying moſt earneſtly vnto oure heauenly father, to ſend his holye ſpirit into our harts, and to endue vs abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dantly with the ſame, that our corrupted and poyſened fleſh, being through it, tamed and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified, we may wholly geue our ſelues to ſerue him, in holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and righteouſneſſe, al the daies of oure liues.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>DyDIMVS.</speaker>
               <p>God graunt it.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶Imprinted at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don by Ihon Tiſdale, and are to be ſold at hys ſhop in Lombard ſtreate.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <p>
               <hi>Cum priuilegio, ad imprimendum ſolum.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1437:89" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
